<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fabulous tales of Esope the Phrygian, compiled moste eloquently in Scottishe metre by Master Robert Henrison, &amp; now lately Englished. ; Euery tale moralized most aptly to this present time, worthy to be read..</title>
            <title>Aesop's fables. English. Selections. 1577</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 186.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S90053</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">54532800</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 54532800</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180704</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00463)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180704)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2125:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fabulous tales of Esope the Phrygian, compiled moste eloquently in Scottishe metre by Master Robert Henrison, &amp; now lately Englished. ; Euery tale moralized most aptly to this present time, worthy to be read..</title>
                  <title>Aesop's fables. English. Selections. 1577</title>
                  <author>Aesop.</author>
                  <author>Henryson, Robert, 1430?-1506?</author>
                  <author>Smith, Richard, fl. 1587.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], [115] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Richard Smith.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Im]printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1577..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>English translation attributed to Richard Smith by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>"Finished in the vale of Aylesburie the thirteenth of August. Anno Domini. 1574."--p. [115].</note>
                  <note>Printers' device on t.p. (McK. 186).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁸, H².</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print bleeding and show-through; cropped, with loss of some page numbers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Animals --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fables --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180704:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180704:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:3"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:3"/> 
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Fabulous tales of Eſope the Phrygian, Compiled moſte eloquently in Scottiſhe Metre by Maſter Robert Henriſon, &amp; now lately Engliſhed.</p>
            <p>Euery tale Moralized moſt aptly to this preſent time, worthy to be read.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>PATET OCCVLTA VERITAS TEMPORE</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Richard Smith. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1577.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:180704:4"/>
            <head>The bookes paſport.</head>
            <l>THat man neare wrote</l>
            <l>whoſe wryte pleaſd all mens mynd,</l>
            <l>Nor I as nowe</l>
            <l>thinke no ſuch place to finde:</l>
            <l>For fyndfault he</l>
            <l>him ſelfe that no good can,</l>
            <l>By ſlaunderous tounge,</l>
            <l>doth hinder many a man,</l>
            <l>Which els would wryte</l>
            <l>to many a ones content:</l>
            <l>(But Bayard I)</l>
            <l>cares not for being ſhent.</l>
            <l>Goe therfore booke,</l>
            <l>to eche mans eye to vewe:</l>
            <l>To wyſe and ſadde,</l>
            <l>and all the carping crewe.</l>
            <l>The wyſeſt ſort,</l>
            <l>will well accept my ſkill:</l>
            <l>Sir Momus mates,</l>
            <l>takes all good things as ill.</l>
            <l>And he that likes not</l>
            <l>this as I do ſay:</l>
            <l>Here is the dore</l>
            <l>and there furth right the way.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:180704:4"/>
            <head>To his worſhipfull and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial good friend Maſter Richard Stoneley Eſquire one of the foure tellers of the Q. Maieſties receyt <hi>of the Eſchecker, and Receiuer of the firſt fruites and tenthes to her Maieſtie.</hi> R. S. <hi>wiſheth encreaſe of Worſhippe to the glorie of God.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Orſhipfull Sir, calling to my minde, that great good will that you haue borne vnto me and mine, ſince the time of my firſt acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with you: except I ſhould be to forgetfull and vngratefull, I muſt remember you, and be as thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as my poore abilitie will ſerue. But the woorme of good will ſtill gnawing my mynde thereto at laſt, all daintie meates and viandes ſet aſide, which are common remembrances, yet vayne and ſoone forgotte, but whyle they are a eating. There came vnto my hande a Scottiſhe Pamphlet, of the Fabulous Tales of Eſope, a worke, ſir as I thinke, in that language wherin it was written, verie eloquent and full of great inuention. And no doubt you ſhall finde ſome ſmatch thereof, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though very rudely I haue obſcured the Authour, and hauing two yeres ſince turned it into Engliſhe, I haue kept it vnpubliſhed, hoping ſome els of greater skill would not haue let it lyen dead. But whether moſt men haue that nation in deriſion for their hollowe hearts and vngratefull mindes to this countrey alwayes had (a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple verie ſubiect to that infection) or thinking ſcorne of the Authour or firſt inuenter, let it paſſe, as friuolous and vaine matter: yet in my conceite there is learning for all
<pb facs="tcp:180704:5"/> ſorts of people worthy the memorie. Therefore knowing not howe by any meanes to let you vnderſtand my good will towarde you, but by this meanes, at laſt putting all feare aſide, I boldly preſent this vnto your worſhip, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that at vacant time when other matters of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance be layde aſide, that you will not deine to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create your minde with this trifle, where you ſhall finde doctrine both pleaſant and profitable, and hoping as oft as you looke on this booke you will thinke on me, accepte this poore Perſian water or Iewes mite, which in ſo doing I care not for all the ſcoffers and taunters, which will do nought themſelues nor ſuffer others to do that may plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or profit the poſteritie. I craue of God to encreaſe you with worldly Worſhippe to his pleaſure.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours at commandement Richard Smith.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translators_foreword">
            <pb facs="tcp:180704:5"/>
            <head>The argument betweene Eſope and the Tranſlatour.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LAte paſſing thorowe Paules Churchyarde,</l>
               <l>aſide I caſt mine eye,</l>
               <l>And ere I wiſt, to me appearde</l>
               <l>Sir <hi>Eſope</hi> by and by,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Apparelled both braue and fine,</l>
               <l>after the Scottiſh guiſe,</l>
               <l>I ſtoode then ſtill with ardent eyne,</l>
               <l>I viewde him twiſe or thriſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Behold quoth he, now am I here,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>and faine would meete ſome one,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſpeake Engliſh that would me leare.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>with that quoth I anone:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why Engliſh Sir, you ſpeake right well,</l>
               <l>what more would you require?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yea thats in proſe: my tales to tell</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>in verſe I do deſire.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alaſſe I am not for your tourne,</l>
               <l>ye muſt repayre vnto</l>
               <l>The Innes of Court and Chauncery,</l>
               <l>where learned haue to do.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:6"/>
               <l>At <hi>Helicon</hi> I neuer came,</l>
               <l>the way I do not knowe,</l>
               <l>(God <hi>Pan</hi> his ſeruant ſir I am,</l>
               <l>and duetie to him owe.)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On oaten pipe we ſtill do play,</l>
               <l>thats all that he teach can,</l>
               <l>Of other lore he takes no way</l>
               <l>this Growtnole ruſticke <hi>Pan.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mineruas</hi> impes they <hi>Orpheus</hi> keepe,</l>
               <l>in Muſicke they delite,</l>
               <l>To ſerue your turne before they ſleepe,</l>
               <l>in verſe to make you dite,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Your Fables wiſe and eloquent,</l>
               <l>with phraſes feate and fine,</l>
               <l>Endewed with <hi>Apollo</hi> gent,</l>
               <l>that paſſeth Muſe of mine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Content your ſelfe quoth Eſope than,</l>
               <l>do thus much once for me,</l>
               <l>To learne me verſe ſo as ye can,</l>
               <l>my ſelfe as playne as ye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They do not care for Scottiſh bookes,</l>
               <l>they liſt not looke that way:</l>
               <l>But if they would but caſt their lookes,</l>
               <l>ſome time when they do play,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:6"/>
               <l>Somewhat to ſee perhaps they might,</l>
               <l>that then would like them wel,</l>
               <l>To teach them treade their way aright,</l>
               <l>to bliſſe, from paines of hel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Farewel good Phrygian Poet now,</l>
               <l>I may no more ſoiourne,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(If not ſayth Eſope) then adew,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Int Scotlande Ile returne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay rather will I venture hard</l>
               <l>and bring your minde to paſſe,</l>
               <l>If that I gaine to my rewarde</l>
               <l>King <hi>Midas</hi> eares of Aſſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And haue a thouſand ill reports</l>
               <l>ſtill tumbling downe on me,</l>
               <l>Than this to want vnto all ſorts</l>
               <l>and view of euery eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore haue here good reader now,</l>
               <l>my rurall ſkilleſſe ſkill,</l>
               <l>I aſke no more but this of you,</l>
               <l>one ynche of your good will,</l>
               <l>Which it to graunt as I do craue,</l>
               <l>thats euen as much as I would haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:7"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>ORpheus</hi> once did walke abrode,</l>
               <l>mong fragrant flowers tencreace his glet,</l>
               <l>To ſet his harpe in one accorde,</l>
               <l>in tune to make his ſtrings agree,</l>
               <l>Whereby was heard ſuch pleaſant ſounde,</l>
               <l>that all the woodes therof rebound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And playing thus in pleaſant ſhade,</l>
               <l>wilde beaſtes and men to him did come:</l>
               <l>With muſicke ſtrayte them ſtones he made,</l>
               <l>his gift was ſuch, them to tranſforme:</l>
               <l>He fell a ſleepe, and or he wooke,</l>
               <l>in hand a while his harpe I tooke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Scottiſh <hi>Orpheus</hi> I meane,</l>
               <l>that <hi>Eſops</hi> tales hath made to gree</l>
               <l>In Rethoricke both trim and cleane,</l>
               <l>that all my wittes bereft hath hee:</l>
               <l>His harpe alas I make to iarre,</l>
               <l>and both his name and mine do marre.</l>
               <l>But ſince I made them diſagree,</l>
               <l>leaue me the blame the Laurel he.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:180704:7"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>The Contentes of the Booke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He tale of the groſſehead Chauntclere the cocke, and the pretious ſtone: wherein is ſhewed the wanton liues of Laſciuious maydes, with the litle care we haue of the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious giftes of God. Fol. 3</item>
                  <item>2 The tale of the plaine country mouſe and daintie town mouſe, wherin is diſplayed our daintie citizens wiues, which can keepe them ſelues in no mediocritie. Fol. 7</item>
                  <item>3 A pleaſant tale of the Cocke and the Foxe, how wily beguiles himſelfe, wherein is to be ſeene the life of the craftie circumucritours of the ſimple men, and yet ſome time how they meete with their match. Fol. 16</item>
                  <item>4 The pleaſant tale howe this falſe diſſembling Tod made his confeſſion to the hypocrite fryer, Wolfe wayt ſkath, that ſheweth the great hypocriſie of the Popiſh prelacie. Fol. 24</item>
                  <item>5 The Rhetoricall tale of the ſonne &amp; heyre of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Tod or Foxe, called father warres, alſo the parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of beaſtes holden by the Lion, which ſhe weth our duetie at all aſſemblies commaunded by our Prince or ſuperiours, &amp; how we ought to behaue our ſelues. 31</item>
                  <item>6 The wofull tale of the plaintife dogge, againſt the poore ſheepe before Iuſtice Wolfe, notably ſhewing the abuſes of ſuch Courtes where money &amp; might maketh the poore to begge. Fol. 44</item>
                  <item>A tale of the Lion &amp; the Mouſe, with the authours prologue before, ſhewing what reuerence we owe to our Princes perſon, yea though he be dead, and howe
<pb facs="tcp:180704:8"/> we ought to venture our liues to do them good. 51</item>
                  <item>8 The notable tale of the preaching of the Swallowe, conteining the office of a preacher and howe they ought to warne vs of Satan his trappes, leſt we be catched in his net. Fol. 62</item>
                  <item>9 The mery tale of the Wolfe that ſayne would haue had the neckeherring or Samon, through the wyles of the Foxe that beguiled the carrier, and of their hard ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures. Fol. 73</item>
                  <item>10 The excellent tale of the wily Laurence Foxe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled the couetous craftie Wolf, where is ſhewed depe diſſembling frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip, &amp; how briberie beareth ſway. 86</item>
                  <item>11 The mery tale of the Wolfe and the Weather, where is painted out the luſty blouds, come vp of low degree by vnlawfull meanes, and apparclling them ſelues in their brauery, wil giue no place to their betters. 94</item>
                  <item>12 The wofull tale of the cruell Wolfe and the innocent Lambe, laying before our ſight the bloud thirſtie tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and oppreſſours of poore helples men. Fol. 101</item>
                  <item>13 The tale of the wofull end of the Paddocke and the Mouſe, ſhewing the well deſerued ende of the holowe harted diſſemblers, and howe God in the ende doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite them. Fol. 107</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly the tranſlators Epilogue, ſhewing that in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed creature God may and wil ſet forth his glorie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180704:8"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>The Argument or Prologue.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>THough fayned Fables of auncient poetry,</l>
               <l>Be not all grounded vpon truth (what than)</l>
               <l>Their politick termes in ſweete Rethory</l>
               <l>Right pleaſaunt are vnto the eare of man,</l>
               <l>And eke the cauſe that they firſt began,</l>
               <l>Was to reproue the hole miſliuing,</l>
               <l>(Of man) by figure of ſome other thing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In like maner thorough the boyſterous erth,</l>
               <l>(So it be labored with great diligence)</l>
               <l>Springs floures and corne to our great myrth,</l>
               <l>Holſome and good to mans ſuſtenaunce.</l>
               <l>So doth ſpring, ſome morall ſweete ſentence,</l>
               <l>Out of the ſubtill dyte of Poetry:</l>
               <l>To good purpoſe, who can it well apply.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The nuttes ſhell though it be hard and tough,</l>
               <l>Holdes the kernell whiche is moſt delectable.</l>
               <l>(So lyes their doctrine wiſe inough,</l>
               <l>And full of fruyte, vnder a fayned fable.)</l>
               <l>And wiſe men ſayes, it is right profitable,</l>
               <l>Amongs erneſt, to mingle merry ſport,</l>
               <l>To recreat the ſpryte, and make the time be ſhort.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Further, the bowe that is ay bent,</l>
               <l>Seemes vnſmart and dui on the ſtring,</l>
               <l>So doth the minde that is ay diligent,</l>
               <l>In earneſt thoughts and great ſtudying,</l>
               <l>With ſad maters ſome myrrineſſe to ming.</l>
               <l>Accordeth well thus Eſope ſayd iwis,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dulcius arrident ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ria picta locis.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of this aucthor my mayſters with your leue,</l>
               <l>Submitting me to your correction:</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:180704:9"/>
               <l> In mother toung, out of Latine to proue</l>
               <l>To make ſome maner of tranſlation,</l>
               <l>Nought of my ſelf, for vayne preſumption,</l>
               <l>But by requeſt, and precept of a Lord,</l>
               <l>Of whom the name I neede not record.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In homely language and in termes rude,</l>
               <l>I needes muſt wryte: for why of Eloquence,</l>
               <l>Nor Rethorike, I neuer vnderſtoode.</l>
               <l>Therefore meekely I pray your reuerence,</l>
               <l>If that ye finde through my negligence,</l>
               <l>To be lacking, or els ſuperfluous,</l>
               <l>Correct it at your willes gratious.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Aucthor in his Fables telles how</l>
               <l>That brutall beaſts ſpake and vnderſtoode,</l>
               <l>And to good purpoſe diſpute and argue.</l>
               <l>And ſillogiſme propone and eke conclude,</l>
               <l>Put in example, and in ſimilitude,</l>
               <l>How many men in operation,</l>
               <l>Are like to beaſtes in condition.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No maruell then, though man be like a beaſt,</l>
               <l>Which loues ay carnall and foule delight,</l>
               <l>That ſhame cannot him pluck backe nor arteſt,</l>
               <l>But takes all his luſt and appetite,</l>
               <l>And that thorow cuſtome and dayly ryte,</l>
               <l>Sinne in their mindes is ſo faſt rooted,</l>
               <l>That they into brutall beaſtes are tranſformed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This noble clerke Eſope, as I haue tolde,</l>
               <l>With great inuention, as poete Laureate,</l>
               <l>By figure wrote his booke: for he nought would</l>
               <l>Lacke the diſdayne of hie, nor low eſtate.</l>
               <l>And to begin, firſt of a Cock he wrate,</l>
               <l>Seeking his meate, which fond a precious ſtone,</l>
               <l>Of whom the Fable ye ſhall heare anone.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="fable">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:180704:9"/>
            <head>The tale of the Groſehead chaunteleare the Cock, and precious Stone.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>A Cocke ſometime with feathers freſh and gay</l>
               <l>Right cant and crowes, albeit he was but poore,</l>
               <l>Flew forth on dunghill early on a day,</l>
               <l>To get his dinner, ſet was all his cure.</l>
               <l>Scraping the mucke, there by aduenture,</l>
               <l>He found a Iaſper ſtone, right pretious,</l>
               <l>Was caſten forth by ſweeping of the houſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As damoſels wanton and inſolent,</l>
               <l>That faine would play, and on the ſtreete be ſeene,</l>
               <l>To ſweeping of the houſe they take no tent</l>
               <l>They care nothing ſo the floore be cleene,</l>
               <l>Iewels are loſt, as ſometime hath bene ſeene</l>
               <l>Vpon the floore, and ſo ſwept forth anone,</l>
               <l>Peraduenture ſo was this pretious ſtone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So marueling vpon this ſtone (quoth he)</l>
               <l>O gentle Iaſp: O ritche and noble thing,</l>
               <l>Though I thee finde, yet art thou not for me,</l>
               <l>Thou art a Iewell for a Lord or King.</l>
               <l>Pitty it were thou ſhould lie in this midding,</l>
               <l>Be buried this amongs this mucke and mold</l>
               <l>And thou ſo fayre and worth ſo mutch gold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It is pittie I ſhould thee finde, for why?</l>
               <l>Thy great vertue nor yet thy colour cleere,</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:180704:10"/>
               <l> It may me nother extoll, nor magnify:</l>
               <l>And thou to me may make but little cheere,</l>
               <l>To great Lords though thou be lief and deere,</l>
               <l>I loue farre better things of leſſe auayle</l>
               <l>As draf or Corne to fill my tuine intrayle.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I had leuer go ſcrape here with my nayles,</l>
               <l>Amongs this muck and looke my liues foode,</l>
               <l>As draf, or corne, ſmall wormes, or ſnayles,</l>
               <l>Or any meate would do my ſtomacke good:</l>
               <l>Than of Iaſper ſtones a mighty multitude.</l>
               <l>And thou againe vpon the ſame wiſe,</l>
               <l>For leſſe auayle thou may me now diſpiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou haſt no corne: and thereof haue I neede,</l>
               <l>Thy colour doth but comfort to the ſight.</l>
               <l>And that is not inough my wombe to feede,</l>
               <l>(For the wiſe ſayes) loking things are light.</l>
               <l>I would haue ſome meate, get it if I might.</l>
               <l>For hungry men may not liue on lookes:</l>
               <l>Had I dry bread, I compt not for no cookes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where ſhould thou make thy habitation?</l>
               <l>Where ſhould thou dwell but in a royall toure?</l>
               <l>Where ſhould thou ſitte but on a kings corone,</l>
               <l>Exalted in worſhip and in great honor?</l>
               <l>Riſe gentell Iaſp, of all ſtones the floure,</l>
               <l>Out of this dunghill and paſſe where thou ſhould be</l>
               <l>Thou cares not for me, nor I for thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Leuing this Iewell loe vpon the ground,</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:180704:10"/>
               <l> To ſeeke his meate this Cock his wayes went,</l>
               <l>But when or how, or by whom it was found,</l>
               <l>As now I ſet to holde no argument.</l>
               <l>But of the inward ſentence, and intent:</l>
               <l>Of this (as mine Author here doth wright)</l>
               <l>I ſhall reherſe in rude and homely dite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This pretious Iaſp, had properties ſeuen,</l>
               <l>The firſt, of colour it was maruelous:</l>
               <l>Parte like the fire, and parte like the heauen,</l>
               <l>It makes a man ſtoute and victorious,</l>
               <l>Preſerues alſo, from chaunces perillous.</l>
               <l>Who hath this ſtone, ſhall haue good hap to ſpeede,</l>
               <l>Nor fire, nor water, he needeth not to dred.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>The Morall.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THis gentle Iaſp right different of hue</l>
                  <l>Betokenith perfect prudence and cunning,</l>
                  <l>Ornate with many deedes of vertue,</l>
                  <l>More excellent, than any earthly thing</l>
                  <l>Whiche makes men in honor for to ring,</l>
                  <l>Happy and ſtoute to winne the victorie,</l>
                  <l>Of all vices and ſpirituall enmitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who may be hardy, ritch, and gratious?</l>
                  <l>Who can eſchue perill and aduenture?</l>
                  <l>Who can gouerne a Realme, Citty or Houſe,</l>
                  <l>Without ſcience, no man I you aſſure?</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:180704:11"/>
                  <l> It is ritches, that euer ſhall endure,</l>
                  <l>Whiche mothe, nor moyſt, nor other ruſt can freat,</l>
                  <l>To mans ſoule it is eternall meat.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Cocke deſireth more the ſimple corne,</l>
                  <l>Than any Iaſpe, (may till a foole be peere)</l>
                  <l>Whiche at ſcience makes a mocke or ſcorne,</l>
                  <l>And no good can, as little will he leare:</l>
                  <l>His hart wambles wiſe argument to heare,</l>
                  <l>As doth a Sowe, to whome men for the nones,</l>
                  <l>Into hir draffe would throw ſome pretious ſtones.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who is enimie to ſcience and cunning,</l>
                  <l>But ignorance that vnderſtandeth nought?</l>
                  <l>Whiche is ſo noble, ſo pretious and ſo digne,</l>
                  <l>That it may not with earthly thing be bought:</l>
                  <l>Well were that man of all other that mought</l>
                  <l>All his life dayes in perfect ſtudy ſpend,</l>
                  <l>To get Science, to keepe him till his end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now (alas) that ſtone is loſt and hide,</l>
                  <l>We ſeeke it not, nor preaſe it not to finde,</l>
                  <l>Haue we ritches, no better life we bide:</l>
                  <l>Of Science though the ſoule be bare and blinde,</l>
                  <l>Of this matter to ſpeake, it were but winde.</l>
                  <l>Therefore I ceaſe, and will no further ſay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(Go ſeeke the Iaſp, who will, for there it lay).</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:180704:11"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>The prety tale of the playne countrey Mouſe, and deyntie towne Mouſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>ESope mine Author maketh mention</l>
               <l>Of two myſe, and they were ſiſters deere,</l>
               <l>Of whome theldeſt dwelt in a Citty or Towne:</l>
               <l>The other dwelte in the countrey there neere,</l>
               <l>Solitary vnder buſhe, ſometime vnder bryer:</l>
               <l>Now in the corne, now in other mens food,</l>
               <l>As theeues do, that liue by others good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This rurall Mouſe, in the winter tyde</l>
               <l>Had hunger, and colde, and alſo great diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>The other Mouſe that in the towne can byde,</l>
               <l>Was a ſworne brother and made a free Burges,</l>
               <l>And had all things toll free, by cuſtome more or leſſe,</l>
               <l>And freedom had to go where euer ſhe liſt,</l>
               <l>Amongs the cheeſe in racke, and meale in chiſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One time when ſhe was full, and longed ſore,</l>
               <l>It came in minde, hir ſiſter for to ſee,</l>
               <l>And where ſhe dwelt, and how hir life ſhe bore,</l>
               <l>And how ſhee farde, vnder the roote of tree:</l>
               <l>Bare foote alone, with ſtaffe ſo goeth ſhee.</l>
               <l>As poore pilgrim, ſhe paſſeth out of towne,</l>
               <l>To ſeeke hir ſiſter, both ore dale and downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Forth many croked wayes, can ſhe walke,</l>
               <l>Throw moſſe and moore, throw banke, buſh &amp; bryer,</l>
               <l>Thus ran ſhe crying, while ſhe came till a balke,</l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:180704:12"/>
               <l> Come forth to me quoth ſhee, myne owne ſiſter deart</l>
               <l>Cry peep Anis, with that the Mouſe could heare,</l>
               <l>And knew hyr voyce, as kinſwomen will do,</l>
               <l>By very kinde, and forth ſhe came hir to.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The harty ioy (O God) if you had ſeene,</l>
               <l>Betweene theſe two ſiſters, when they mette,</l>
               <l>And great loue was ſhewen them betweene,</l>
               <l>For whiles they laugh, and whyles for ioy they wept,</l>
               <l>Somwhiles kiſſing ſweete, ſomwhiles in armes replet</l>
               <l>And thus they fare, while ſoberd was there moode,</l>
               <l>So foote for foote, vnto the chamber yoode.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As I hard ſay, hit was a ſimple one,</l>
               <l>Of fog and ſerue full feebly was made,</l>
               <l>A homely thing, ouer a ſtedfaſt ſtone,</l>
               <l>Of whiche thentrie, was not hie nor brode,</l>
               <l>And in they went, withouten more abode,</l>
               <l>Without fier or candle, burnyng bright,</l>
               <l>For commonly, ſuch pickers loues no light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When they weare lodged thus, theſe ſilly myce,</l>
               <l>The yongeſt ſiſter into her buttery glyd,</l>
               <l>And brought foorth nuttes and corne in ſteede of ſpice,</l>
               <l>If this weare good I aſke you here beſide,</l>
               <l>The towne Mouſe, promped forth in pryde,</l>
               <l>And ſayd ſiſter, is this your dayly foode?</l>
               <l>Why not (quoth ſhe) is not this meate right good?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay by my ſoule I take it but in ſkorne,</l>
               <l>Madam (quoth ſhe) ye be the more to blame,</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:180704:12"/>
               <l> My mother ſayd ſiſter, when we were borne,</l>
               <l>That I and ye lay both within on wame,</l>
               <l>I keepe the rate and cuſtome of my Dame,</l>
               <l>And alwayes liues, thus in pouertie,</l>
               <l>For landes haue we none in propertie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My fayre ſiſter (quoth ſhe) haue me excuſed,</l>
               <l>This rude diet and I cannot accord,</l>
               <l>To tender meat my ſtomake is ay vſed,</l>
               <l>For whyles I fare aſwell as any Lord,</l>
               <l>Theſe withered peaſe, and nuttes or they be bord,</l>
               <l>Will breake my teeth, &amp; make my wombe ful ſlender,</l>
               <l>Whiche was before vſed to meates ſo tender.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well well ſiſter, (quoth the countrey mouſe,)</l>
               <l>If it pleaſe you ſuch things as ye ſee there,</l>
               <l>Both meate and drinke, my lodging and houſe,</l>
               <l>Shalbe your owne whyles ye remaynen heare.</l>
               <l>Ye ſhall it haue with myrth and merry cheare,</l>
               <l>And that ſhould make the meaſes that are rude,</l>
               <l>Among friends, right tender and wounders good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What pleaſure is, in feaſts delicate,</l>
               <l>The whiche are geuen with a lowring browe?</l>
               <l>A gentle hart is better recreate,</l>
               <l>With harty minde, than ſet to him a kowe.</l>
               <l>A modicum, is more for to allowe,</l>
               <l>So that good will be caruer at the deaſe,</l>
               <l>Than coſtly fayre and many ſpiced meaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For all hir good will, and mery exhortation</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:180704:13"/>
               <l> This Burges mouſe had little luſt to ſing,</l>
               <l>But heauyly ſhe caſt hir browes a downe,</l>
               <l>For all the daynties that ſhe could hir bring:</l>
               <l>Yet at the laſt, ſhe ſayd halfe in ſkorning,</l>
               <l>Siſter this victuall, and your royall feaſt,</l>
               <l>May well ſuffice vnto a rurall geaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let alone this hole, and come now me after,</l>
               <l>And I ſhall to you ſhewe by experience,</l>
               <l>That my good Fryday is better than your Eſter,</l>
               <l>My diſhe lickings, is worth your hole expence,</l>
               <l>I haue houſes moe, of great defence,</l>
               <l>Of Cat nor trap, iwis I haue no dreede:</l>
               <l>I graunt, quoth ſhe, and on together yeede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In ſtubble array thorow graſſe and corne:</l>
               <l>And vnder buſſhes priuily can they creepe,</l>
               <l>Theldeſt was the guyde and went beforne,</l>
               <l>The yonger to hir wayes tooke good keepe:</l>
               <l>On night they ran, and on the day can ſleepe,</l>
               <l>And early in the morning, ere they blin,</l>
               <l>They fand the towne, and meryly went in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not farre fro thence into a fayre place,</l>
               <l>This Burges brought the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoone where they ſhould be,</l>
               <l>Without God ſpeede, their lodging there they haſe,</l>
               <l>Into a ſpence with victall great plenty,</l>
               <l>Both cheeſe and butter vpon the ſhelues hie,</l>
               <l>And fleſh and fiſh inough, bothe freſhe and ſalt,</l>
               <l>And ſackes full of meale and eke of malt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:180704:13"/>
               <l>After, when they were diſpoſed to dine,</l>
               <l>Without grace they waſh, and went to meate.</l>
               <l>With all courſes that Cookes could deuiſe,</l>
               <l>As Mutton and Beef layde in chardgers great:</l>
               <l>Yea Lordes fare thus could they counterfeat,</l>
               <l>Except one thing, they dranke the water cleare,</l>
               <l>In ſteede of wine, but yet they made good cheere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With face vp caſt and mery countenaunce,</l>
               <l>The eldeſt ſiſter ſpake vnto hir geſt,</l>
               <l>If that ſhe by reaſon, fond difference</l>
               <l>Betwixt that chamber and hir ſory neſt:</l>
               <l>Yea dame (quoth ſhe) how long wil this leſt?</l>
               <l>For euermore I wote, and longer to,</l>
               <l>If it be ſo, ye are at caſe (quoth ſhoe).</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To all this cheere a banquet forth ſhee brought,</l>
               <l>A plate of grotes and a diſhe of meale,</l>
               <l>Ote cakes alſo I trow, ſhe ſpared nought,</l>
               <l>Abundantly about hir for to deale.</l>
               <l>And manfully ſo, ſhe brought in ſteede of geill,</l>
               <l>A white candle, out of a coffer ſtale,</l>
               <l>In ſteede of ſpice to taſte their mouths withall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This made they mery while they might no more,</l>
               <l>All hayle all hayle, cried ſhe on hie,</l>
               <l>Yet after ioy oft times comes matter ſore,</l>
               <l>And trouble after great proſperitie:</l>
               <l>Thus as they ſate in all their iolitie</l>
               <l>The ſpencer comes, with keyes in his hand,</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:180704:14"/>
               <l> Opened the dore and them at dinner fande.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They taried not to waſhe as I ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>But on to go who that mought formoſt winne,</l>
               <l>The towne mouſe had an hole and in ſhe goes,</l>
               <l>Hir ſiſter had no hole to hide hir in,</l>
               <l>To ſee that ſelly mouſe it were great ſinne</l>
               <l>So deſolate there and harde beſtead,</l>
               <l>For very dred ſhe fell in fowne neare dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But as God would it fell an happy caſe,</l>
               <l>The Spencer had no leyſure for to byde,</l>
               <l>Nother to ſeeke nor ſearch to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ere ne chaſe,</l>
               <l>But on he went and left the dore vp wide?</l>
               <l>This bolde Burges this paſſing well hath ſpied,</l>
               <l>Out of hir hole ſhe came and cried on hie:</l>
               <l>How fare ye ſiſter crie peep where ere ye be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This rurall mouſe, lay flatling on the ground,</l>
               <l>For feare of death ſhe was full ſore dredand.</l>
               <l>For to hir hart ſtrake many wofull ſound,</l>
               <l>As in a feuer ſhe trimbled foote and hand,</l>
               <l>And when hir ſiſter in ſuch plight her fand,</l>
               <l>For very pitty ſhe began to weepe:</l>
               <l>So comforted hir with woordes hony and ſweete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why lie ye thus ryſe vp my ſiſter deare?</l>
               <l>Come to your meate this perrill is or epaſt,</l>
               <l>The other anſwered hir with heauy cheare,</l>
               <l>I may not eate, ſo ſore I am agaſt,</l>
               <l>I had leuer this fortie dayes to faſt,</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:180704:14"/>
               <l> With water porrage, and to gnaw beanes or peaſe,</l>
               <l>Than all your feaſt in this dread and deſeaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With faire treaty yet ſhe made hir ryſe,</l>
               <l>And to the boord they went, and togither ſate,</l>
               <l>And ſcantly had they dronken once or twyſe,</l>
               <l>When in came Gib hunter, our ioly Cat</l>
               <l>And bad Godſpeede, the Burges vp with that,</l>
               <l>And till hir hole ſhe went as fire of flint,</l>
               <l>But Gilbert the other by the backe has hint.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From foote to foote he caſt hyr ſo with puſſhes,</l>
               <l>Now vp now downe, now ſuffer hir to creepe</l>
               <l>Now would he let her run vnder the ruſhes</l>
               <l>Now would he winke and play with hir bo peep</l>
               <l>Thus to the ſilly mouſe he did paynes grete:</l>
               <l>Whyles at the laſt thorow fortune and good hap,</l>
               <l>Betwixt a bord and the wall ſhe crap.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And vp in haſt behinde the cloth paynted,</l>
               <l>She clam ſo hie that Gilbert might not get hir</l>
               <l>There by the cludges craftely ſhe hanged,</l>
               <l>Till he was gone, hir cheare was all the better,</l>
               <l>So downe ſhe lap when there was none to let her,</l>
               <l>And to the Burges mouſe lowde can ſhe crie,</l>
               <l>Fare well fayre ſiſter thy feaſtes here I defie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy feaſtings are filled all with care,</l>
               <l>Thy guyſe is good, thend is ſower as gall</l>
               <l>The ſubchardge of thy ſeruices is fayre fare,</l>
               <l>So that thou finde hereafter warde no fall</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:180704:15"/>
               <l> I thanke you curtaines, and you purple wall,</l>
               <l>Of my defence, now from you cruell beaſt,</l>
               <l>Almighty God keepe me fro ſuch another feaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Were I into the cabin, that I came fro,</l>
               <l>For weale nor wo ſhould I neare come agayne.</l>
               <l>With that ſhe tooke hir leaue, and forth can go,</l>
               <l>Somtimes throw y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> corne &amp; ſomtimes throw y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>When ſhe was forth and free ſhe was full fayne:</l>
               <l>And merely marched vnto the moore,</l>
               <l>I cannot tell how there ſhe foore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But I hearde ſay ſhe paſſed to hir denne,</l>
               <l>As warme as woll, ſuppoſe it was not great,</l>
               <l>Full well ſtuffed at eche ſide and ende</l>
               <l>With beanes, and nuttes, peaſe, rye, and wheat:</l>
               <l>When euer ſhe luſt ſhe had inough to cate,</l>
               <l>In quiet and reſt, without any dread,</l>
               <l>But to hir ſiſters feaſt, nomore ſhe yead.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>FRendes, ye may finde and ye will take heede,</l>
                  <l>In this Fable a good Moralitie:</l>
                  <l>As fitches mingled are with noble ſeede,</l>
                  <l>So intermingled is aduerſitie</l>
                  <l>With earthly ioy, ſo that no ſtate is free</l>
                  <l>Without trouble and ſome vexation,</l>
                  <l>As namely they whiche clime vp moſt hie,</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:180704:15"/>
                  <l> That are not content with ſmall poſſeſſion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bleſſed be the ſimple life without dread,</l>
                  <l>Bleſſed be ſober feaſt in quietie:</l>
                  <l>Who hath inough, of no more hath he neede,</l>
                  <l>Though that it be little in quantitie:</l>
                  <l>Great aboundance and blinde proſperitie,</l>
                  <l>Ofttimes makes an euil concluſion:</l>
                  <l>The ſweeteſt life therefore in this countrie,</l>
                  <l>Is a contented minde with ſmall poſſeſſion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O wanton man, that vſeſt for to feede</l>
                  <l>Thy wombe and makes it a God to be,</l>
                  <l>Like to thy ſelf, I warne thee wele to dreede,</l>
                  <l>The Cat comes, and to the mouſe hies he,</l>
                  <l>What auayles than thy feaſt and royaltie,</l>
                  <l>With dreadfull hart and tribulation?</l>
                  <l>Beſt thing in earth, therefore I ſay for me,</l>
                  <l>Is content in hart, with ſmall poſſeſſion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thine owne fire is beſt my frende; if thou take heede,</l>
                  <l>It warmes well, and is worth gold to thee:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth, if that thou wilt reede</l>
                  <l>Vnder the Heauen there cannot better bee,</l>
                  <l>Then for to be mery, and liue in honeſty.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore I may conclude by this reaſon,</l>
                  <l>Of earthly ioy it is the beſt degree,</l>
                  <l>A hart contented with ſmall poſſeſſion.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:180704:16"/>
            <head>The pleaſant tale of the Coc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and the Foxe how wyly beguyles him ſelfe.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THough brutall beaſts be irrationall,</l>
               <l>That is to ſay wanting diſcretion,</l>
               <l>Yet euery man in their kinde naturall,</l>
               <l>Hath many and diuers inclination.</l>
               <l>The boyſtrous Beare, the Wolf, the wilde Lion:</l>
               <l>The Foxe feyning, crafty, and cautelous:</l>
               <l>The dogge to barke on nights and keepe the houſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So different they are in properties,</l>
               <l>Vnknowen to man and ſo infinite,</l>
               <l>In kinde hauing ſo fell diuerſities,</l>
               <l>My cunning is excluded for to endite.</l>
               <l>Of them as now I purpoſe not to wryte</l>
               <l>A caſe I fand whiche fell this other day,</l>
               <l>Betwixt a Fox and a Cock full gay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A wydow dwelt in a cottage many dayes,</l>
               <l>Whiche ernd hir foode with ſpinning on hir rocke,</l>
               <l>And no more had forſoth, as the Fable ſayes,</l>
               <l>Except of hennes ſhe had a little flocke,</l>
               <l>And them to keepe ſhe had a iolly Cock:</l>
               <l>Right couragious, that to this widow ay,</l>
               <l>Deuided the night, and crowde before the day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A little from this foreſayd widdowes houſe,</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:180704:16"/>
               <l> A thorny thicket there was of greate defence,</l>
               <l>Wherein a Foxe crafty and cautelous,</l>
               <l>Made his abode and dayly reſidence,</l>
               <l>Whiche to this widowe did great violence,</l>
               <l>In picking of pultry bothe day and night,</l>
               <l>And no way be reuenged on him ſhe might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This wyly Foxe when that the Larcke could ſing,</l>
               <l>Full ſore hungry vntill the towne him dreſt,</l>
               <l>Where this luſty Cock in the gray morning,</l>
               <l>Weary of night was flowen fro his neſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> this ſaw, and in his minde keſt</l>
               <l>The ieoperdy, the wayes, and the wyle,</l>
               <l>By what meanes he mought the Cock beguile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Diſſimuling in countenance and cheere,</l>
               <l>On knees fell, and flattering thus he ſayd:</l>
               <l>Good morne my mayſter gentle Chauntcleere.</l>
               <l>With that the Cock ſtart backward in abrayd:</l>
               <l>Sir by my ſoule ye neede not be affrayd,</l>
               <l>Nor yet for me to ſtart nor flee abacke,</l>
               <l>For I come hither ſeruice to you to make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Would I not ſerue you, I were to blame,</l>
               <l>As I haue done to your progenitor:</l>
               <l>Your father full oft filled hath my wame,</l>
               <l>And ſent me meate from donghill to the moore,</l>
               <l>And at his ende I did my buſie cure</l>
               <l>To holde his head and giue him drinkes warme,</l>
               <l>So at the laſt he ſounded in my arme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:180704:17"/>
               <l>Knew ye my Father (quoth the Cock) and lough,</l>
               <l>Yea my fayre Sonne, I helde vp his head,</l>
               <l>When that he died vnder a byrchen bongh.</l>
               <l>And ſayd the Diridge when that he was dead:</l>
               <l>Betwixt vs two how ſhould there be any fead?</l>
               <l>Whom ſhould ye truſt but me your ſeruitour,</l>
               <l>That to your Father did ſo great honour?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When I behelde your feathers fayre and gent,</l>
               <l>Your beake, your breſt, your hekell and your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome,</l>
               <l>Sir by my ſoule and the bleſſed Sacrament,</l>
               <l>My hart is warme, me thinkes I am at home:</l>
               <l>To make you mery I would creepe on my wome,</l>
               <l>In froſt and ſnow, in weather wan and neate,</l>
               <l>And lay my golden lockes vnder your feete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This fayned Foxe falſe and diſſimulate,</l>
               <l>Made to this Cock a crafty cauillation:</l>
               <l>Yee are me thinkes changd and degenerate,</l>
               <l>From your Father of his condition,</l>
               <l>Of crafty crowing he might beare the crowne:</l>
               <l>For he would on his toes ſlande and craw,</l>
               <l>This was no lie, I ſtoode beſide and ſaw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that the Cock vpon his toes hie,</l>
               <l>Keſt vp his booke, and ſang with all his might,</l>
               <l>Quoth ſir <hi>Laurence</hi> well ſayde ſo mote I thee,</l>
               <l>Yee are your fathers Sonne and heyre vpright:</l>
               <l>But of his cunning yet ye want one ſlight,</l>
               <l>For (quoth the Tod) he would withouten dont,</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:180704:17"/>
               <l> Both winke, and crowe, &amp; turne him thrice about.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Cock infect with winde and falſe vayneglore,</l>
               <l>That many puts vnto confuſion,</l>
               <l>Truſting to winne great worſhip therefore,</l>
               <l>Vnwarely winked walking vp and doune,</l>
               <l>And ſo to ſing and crowe he made him boune:</l>
               <l>And ſodainly by he had crowne a note,</l>
               <l>The Foxe was ware, and catchd him by the throte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So to the wood without tarrying he hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d,</l>
               <l>Of that crime hauing but little doubte,</l>
               <l>With that Pertoke, Spratoke, and Toppoke cried.</l>
               <l>The widow heard; and with a crie came out,</l>
               <l>Seing the caſe, ſhe ſight and gaue a ſhoute.</l>
               <l>With how murthrer hay, and gaue hir dore a knocke,</l>
               <l>Saying now alas, loſt is my gentle Cock.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As ſhe were wood with many yell and crie,</l>
               <l>Pulling hir heare, vpon hir breaſt can beate,</l>
               <l>So pale of hue halfe in an extaſie,</l>
               <l>Fell downe for care in ſowning and in ſweate:</l>
               <l>With that the ſilly hennes lefte their meate,</l>
               <l>And whyleſt their dame lay thus in ſowne,</l>
               <l>They all fell into diſputation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas (quoth Pertok) making ſore monyng,</l>
               <l>With teares great, whiche downe hir cheekes fell,</l>
               <l>Yonder was our le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>man and our dayes darlyng,</l>
               <l>Our Nightingall, and our mornyng bell,</l>
               <l>Our walking watch vs for to warne and tell,</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:180704:18"/>
               <l> When that <hi>Aurora</hi> with hir courſers gray,</l>
               <l>Put vp hir head betwixt the night and day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who ſhall our lemman be? who ſhall vs leade?</l>
               <l>When we are ſad, who ſhall vnto vs ſing?</l>
               <l>With his ſweete bill, he would breake vs the bread,</l>
               <l>In all this world there was no kinder thing,</l>
               <l>In paramory he would do vs pleaſing,</l>
               <l>To his power as nature did him giue:</l>
               <l>Now after him alas, how ſhall we liue?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quoth Sprucock then, ceaſe ſiſter of your ſorrow,</l>
               <l>Ye be to madde ſuch mourning for to gloſe,</l>
               <l>We ſhall ſpeede well I finde S. Iohn to borrow:</l>
               <l>The Prouerbe ſayes, as good loues comes as goes,</l>
               <l>I will put on my holydaye clothes,</l>
               <l>And make me freſhe againſt this iolly May,</l>
               <l>So ſing this ſong, <hi>was neuer widow ſo gay.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He was angry, and helde vs ay in awe,</l>
               <l>And wounded with the ſpeare of ielouſie,</l>
               <l>Of chamber glue Pertoke, full well yee know,</l>
               <l>Waſted he was, of nature colde and dry.</l>
               <l>Since he is gone, therefore ſiſter ſay I,</l>
               <l>Put care away, for that is beſt remead,</l>
               <l>Let quicke to quicke, and dead goe to the dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then Pertoke ſpake, with fayned fayth before,</l>
               <l>In luſt without loue he ſet all his delight:</l>
               <l>Siſter ye wote, of ſuch as him a ſcore,</l>
               <l>Would not ſuffiſe to ſlake our appetite,</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:180704:18"/>
               <l> I holde here my hande ſince he is quite,</l>
               <l>Within a myle for ſhame and I durſt ſpeeke,</l>
               <l>To get a lad ſhould better clawe our breeke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Than Toppok like a prieſt ſpake full crous,</l>
               <l>You was a very vengeance from the heauen,</l>
               <l>He was ſo lowſe and ſo lecherous.</l>
               <l>He had (quoth ſhe) Kittoks more than ſeuen:</l>
               <l>But rightuous God holding the ballance euen,</l>
               <l>Smytes right ſore though he be patient,</l>
               <l>For adultery, that will them not repent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Full of pryde he was, and ioyed in his ſinne,</l>
               <l>And counted not for Gods fauour nor fayth,</l>
               <l>But truſted all to riot and ſo did rinne:</l>
               <l>While at laſt his ſinnes can him ſkayth,</l>
               <l>To ſhamefull ende, and to you ſodden death.</l>
               <l>Therefore it is the very hand of God,</l>
               <l>That cauſeth him, be werried with the Tod.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When this was ſayd, this widow from hir ſowne,</l>
               <l>Stert vp on foote and on the dogges ſhe cryed,</l>
               <l>How bercke, bery, bowſie, browne,</l>
               <l>Ripe ſhaw, run well, curteys, nutticlyde,</l>
               <l>Together all without grudging ſee ye ſpeede,</l>
               <l>Reſcue my noble Cock or he be ſlayne,</l>
               <l>Or els to me, ſee ye come neuer againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Withouten more for feare of being ſhent,</l>
               <l>As fier of flint ouer the fieldes flawe,</l>
               <l>Full ſwiftly thorow woodes and waters went,</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:180704:19"/>
               <l> And ceaſed not ſir <hi>Laurence</hi> till they ſawe:</l>
               <l>But when he ſaw the houndes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on a rawe,</l>
               <l>Vnto the Cock in minde he ſayde God ſen,</l>
               <l>That I and thou were preſent in my den.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſayd the Cocke with ſome good ſprite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſpirit,</l>
               <l>Do my counſell, and I ſhall warrant thei:</l>
               <l>Hungry thou art, and for great trauayle tyred,</l>
               <l>Right faynt of force, and may not further flee:</l>
               <l>Quickly turne againe, and ſay that I and yet,</l>
               <l>Frendes are made, and fellowes for a yeere,</l>
               <l>Then will they ſtint, Ile ſtande betweene ye heere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus Tod though he was falſe and friuolous,</l>
               <l>And had craft his quarell to defend,</l>
               <l>Deceyued was by meanes right maruelous,</l>
               <l>For wyly beguiles himſelfe at the latter end:</l>
               <l>He ſtart abacke and cried as he was lernd,</l>
               <l>With that the Cock flew vp into a tree,</l>
               <l>Now whether ſir <hi>Laurence</hi> laugh or no iudge yee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beguyled thus the Tod vnder the tree,</l>
               <l>On knees fell, and ſayd good Chaunteclere:</l>
               <l>Come downe agayne, and without meate or fee,</l>
               <l>Ile be your man, and ſerue you for a yeere.</l>
               <l>No falſe theefe and rouer, ſtand not me neere.</l>
               <l>My bloudy combe and my necke ſo ſore,</l>
               <l>Hath parted frendſhip, twixt vs for euermore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I was vnwiſe that winked at thy will,</l>
               <l>Where thorow almoſt I loſed had my head,</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:180704:19"/>
               <l> I was more foole (quoth he) to be ſo ſtill,</l>
               <l>Where thorow to put my pray now into plead.</l>
               <l>Away falſe theefe, God keepe me fro thy fead.</l>
               <l>With that the Cock ouer the fieldes tooke flight,</l>
               <l>And in at the widowes window could he light.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOw worthy folke, ſuppoſe this be a Fable,</l>
                  <l>And ouerheled with tipes fugerall,</l>
                  <l>Yet may ye finde ſome ſentence right agreeable,</l>
                  <l>Vnder theſe fayned termes textuall.</l>
                  <l>To our purpoſe this Cock well may we call,</l>
                  <l>Nice proude men, voyde and vaine glorious,</l>
                  <l>Of kin and bloud, which are preſumptuous.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Fie puft vp pryde, thou art full poyſonable,</l>
                  <l>Who fauoureth thee of force muſt haue a fall,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſtrength is nought, thy ſtoole ſtands vnſtable.</l>
                  <l>Take witneſſe of the fendes infernall,</l>
                  <l>Whiche throwen downe were from the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly hal</l>
                  <l>To Hels hole and to that hideous houſe,</l>
                  <l>Bicauſe in pryde, they were preſumptuous.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This fayned Foxe may well be figurate,</l>
                  <l>To flatterers with pleaſant woordes white,</l>
                  <l>With falſe meaning and minde moſt toxicate,</l>
                  <l>To gloſe and lie, that ſettes their whole delite,</l>
                  <l>All worthy folke, at ſuch ſhould haue deſpite.</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:180704:20"/>
                  <l> For where is there more perillous peſtilence,</l>
                  <l>Than giue to lyars haſty credence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The wicked minde and adulation,</l>
                  <l>Of theſe ſweete ſuckers hauing the ſimilitude,</l>
                  <l>Are bitter as gall, and full of poyſon,</l>
                  <l>To taſt it is, who cleerely vnderſtoode:</l>
                  <l>For this as now ſhortly to conclude,</l>
                  <l>Theſe two ſinnes, flattery and vaineglore,</l>
                  <l>(Are perilous) good folke flee them therefore.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <head>¶ <hi>The pleaſant tale howe this falſe diſſembling Tod, made his confeſſion to the hypocrite fryer Wolfe, Waytſkayth.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>LEauing this wydow glad I you aſſure,</l>
               <l>Of Chauntclere more iocund than I can tell:</l>
               <l>And ſpeake we of the ſubtill aduenture,</l>
               <l>And deſtinit that to this Foxe befell,</l>
               <l>Whiche durſt no more with wayting intermell,</l>
               <l>As long as leame or light was of the day,</l>
               <l>But byding night full ſtill lurking he lay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whyle that the Goddoſſe of the flood,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phebus</hi> had called to the harbery,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Heſperus</hi> put vp his clowdy hood,</l>
               <l>Shewing his iuſty viſage in the ſkie.</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:180704:20"/>
               <l> Then <hi>Laurence</hi> looked vp where he did lie,</l>
               <l>And caſt his hande vpon his eye on hight,</l>
               <l>Mery and glad that come was the night.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Out of the woodde vnto a hill he went,</l>
               <l>Where he mought ſee the twinekling ſtarres cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re,</l>
               <l>And all the Planets of the firmament,</l>
               <l>Theyr courſe and eke their mouing in the ſphere:</l>
               <l>Some Retrograde, and ſome Stationere:</l>
               <l>And of the Zodiake in what degree,</l>
               <l>They were eche one as <hi>Laurence</hi> learned mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then <hi>Saturne</hi> olde was entred in <hi>Capricorne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Iuppiter</hi> moued in <hi>Sagittarie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Mars</hi> in the <hi>Rams</hi> head was borne,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Phebus</hi> in the <hi>Lion</hi> forth can carrie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> the <hi>Crab,</hi> the <hi>Mone</hi> was in <hi>Aquarie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> the God of <hi>Eloquence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Into the <hi>Virgin</hi> made his reſidence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Without Aſtrolab, Quadrant, or Almanake,</l>
               <l>Taught of nature by inſtruction,</l>
               <l>The mouing of the heauen this Tod can take,</l>
               <l>What influence and conſtellation,</l>
               <l>Was like to fall vpon the earth adowne.</l>
               <l>And to himſelfe he ſayd this one thing,</l>
               <l>God haue me Father that ſet me to learning.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My deſteny and eke my death is knowne,</l>
               <l>My aduenture is clearely to me kend,</l>
               <l>With miſchiefe mortall men are ouerthrowne,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:21"/>
               <l> My miſſyning the ſooner but if I mend,</l>
               <l>It is rewarde of ſinne, a ſhamefull end.</l>
               <l>Therefore I will go ſeeke ſome confeſſoure,</l>
               <l>And ſhryue me cleane of my ſinnes to this houre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And (quoth he) right fearfull are wee theeues,</l>
               <l>Our liues be eche night in aduenture,</l>
               <l>Our curſed crafte full many men miſchieues:</l>
               <l>For euer we ſteale, and ouer are like poore,</l>
               <l>In dread and ſhame our dayes we endure.</l>
               <l>Still hunting after miſchief at euery becke,</l>
               <l>Till at laſt for our hyre we are hanged by the necke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Accurſing thus his cankred conſcience,</l>
               <l>On top of a crag he caſt aboute his eye,</l>
               <l>And ſaw comming a little from thence,</l>
               <l>A worthy Docter in diuinitie,</l>
               <l>Fryer Wolfe Waytſkayth, in ſcience wonders ſlie,</l>
               <l>To preach and pray was commen from the cloſter,</l>
               <l>With heades in hand, ſaying his <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Seyng this Wolf this wyly traytor Tod,</l>
               <l>On knees fell with hood into his necke,</l>
               <l>Welcome my ghoſtly father vnder God,</l>
               <l>(Quoth he) with many bow, and many becke,</l>
               <l>Ha (quoth the Wolf) ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tod for what effect,</l>
               <l>Make ye ſuch mone, riſe vp on your foet?</l>
               <l>Father, quoth he, I haue great cauſe to doet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ye are Mirrour, Lanterne, and liuely way,</l>
               <l>To guyde ſuth ſimple men as me to grace,</l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:180704:21"/>
               <l> Your barefeete, and your u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nle of grey.</l>
               <l>Your leane cheekes, your pale pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous face,</l>
               <l>Whiche ſhewes to me your perfect holineſſe,</l>
               <l>For well were him that once in his liue,</l>
               <l>Had hap to you, his ſinnes for to ſhryne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay ſilly <hi>Laurence</hi> (quoth the Wolf) and lough,</l>
               <l>It pleaſeth me that ye are penitent.</l>
               <l>Of theft and flouth, ſir I can tell inough,</l>
               <l>That cauſeth me full ſore for to repent:</l>
               <l>But Father byde ſtill here vpon the bent,</l>
               <l>I you beſeech, and heare mee to deplore,</l>
               <l>My guiltie conſcience that prickes me ſo ſore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well, quoth the Wolf, ſit downe vpon thy knee,</l>
               <l>And he downe barehead ſate full humily,</l>
               <l>And ſo began with <hi>Benedicitee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When I this ſaw I drewe a little by,</l>
               <l>For it is no good manners to heare nor ſpie,</l>
               <l>Nor to reueale things ſayde vnder that ſeale,</l>
               <l>Yet to the Tods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, the Wolf did thus appeale</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Art thou contrite and ſory in thy ſpryte,</l>
               <l>For thy treſpas? nay ſir I cannot doet,</l>
               <l>My thinkes that hennes are ſo hony ſweete,</l>
               <l>And Lambes fleſh that new are letten blood,</l>
               <l>For to repent my minde cannot conclude:</l>
               <l>But of this thing, that I haue ſlayne ſo few,</l>
               <l>Well, quoth the Wolf, in ſayth thou art a ſhrew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Since thou cannot forethinke thy wickedneſſe,</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:180704:22"/>
               <l> Wilt thou forbeare in time to come and mende?</l>
               <l>And I forbeare, how ſhould I liue alas?</l>
               <l>Hauing no other crafte me to defende,</l>
               <l>Neede cauſeth me to ſteale where euer I wende:</l>
               <l>I ſhame to begge, and worke I ne can,</l>
               <l>Yet would I fayne, pretende a Gentleman.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well (quoth the Wolfe) thou wantes points two,</l>
               <l>That belong to perfect confeſſion:</l>
               <l>To the third part of penitence let vs go.</l>
               <l>Wilt thou take paynes for thy tranſgreſſion?</l>
               <l>Nay ſir, conſider my complexion,</l>
               <l>Sielly and weake, and of my nature tender,</l>
               <l>Lo, will yee ſee, I am both leaue and ſlender.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet neuertheleſſe I would ſo it were light,</l>
               <l>Shorte and not greeuing to my tenderneſſe,</l>
               <l>Take parte of payne, fulfill it if I might,</l>
               <l>To ſet my ſilly ſoule in way of grace:</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt (quoth he) forbeare fleſh vntill Paſe,</l>
               <l>To tame thy corps that curſed carrion:</l>
               <l>And here I giue thee full remiſſion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I graunt thereto, ſo ye will giue me leaue,</l>
               <l>To eate puddings, or lap a little blood,</l>
               <l>Or head, or feete, or panches let me preue,</l>
               <l>In caſe I fall no fleſhe vnto my food:</l>
               <l>For great neede. I giue thee leaue good,</l>
               <l>Twiſe in the weeke, for neede may haue no law:</l>
               <l>God thanke you ſir, for that text well I knaw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:180704:22"/>
               <l>When this was ſayd, the Wolf his wayes went,</l>
               <l>The Foxe a foote he goth vnto the flood,</l>
               <l>To get him fiſhe, hollily was his intent:</l>
               <l>But when he ſaw the water and waues wood,</l>
               <l>Aſtoniſht all, ſtill in a muſe he ſtood:</l>
               <l>And ſayd, better that I had bidden at hame,</l>
               <l>Nor bene a fiſher in the Deuils name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now muſt I ſcrape my meate out of the flood,</l>
               <l>And I haue nother bootes nor yet boat.</l>
               <l>As he was thus for faulte of meate neare wood,</l>
               <l>Looking about like a wyly ſoat,</l>
               <l>Vnder a tree he ſaw a trip of goate,</l>
               <l>Than was he mery, and through the hedge him hid,</l>
               <l>And from the goate, he ſtale hir little kid.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So ouer the hedge vnto the water hies,</l>
               <l>And tooke the kidde by the hornes twayne,</l>
               <l>And in the water either twiſe or thryſe,</l>
               <l>He dowked him, and to him can he ſayne:</l>
               <l>Go downe ſir kid, come vp ſir Salmon againe.</l>
               <l>While he was dead ſo to the lande him drough,</l>
               <l>And of that new made Salmon he eate inough.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus finely filled with yong tender meate,</l>
               <l>Vnto a thicket for dread he him adreſt,</l>
               <l>Vnder a buſh, where the Sunne can beate,</l>
               <l>To beyke his breſt and belly he thought beſt,</l>
               <l>And ſcorningly, he ſayde, where he did reſt,</l>
               <l>Stroking his wombe againſt the Sunnes heate,</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:180704:23"/>
               <l> Vpon this belly, what if a bolt ſhould beate?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When this was ſayd, the keeper of the gayt,</l>
               <l>Carefull in hart, his kid was ſtolne away,</l>
               <l>On euery ſide full warely could he wayt,</l>
               <l>Till at the laſt he ſaw where <hi>Laurence</hi> lay:</l>
               <l>A bowe he bent, an arrow with feathers gray,</l>
               <l>He drew to the head, and or he ſtearth,</l>
               <l>The Foxe he pricketh faſt vnto the earth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now, quoth the Foxe, alas and well away,</l>
               <l>Gored I am and may no further go,</l>
               <l>Me thinkes no man may ſpeake a woorde in play,</l>
               <l>But now adayes in earneſt its turned ſo,</l>
               <l>He tooke him and his arrow drew him fro.</l>
               <l>And for his Kid and other violence,</l>
               <l>He tooke his ſkinne and made a recompence.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THis ſudden death, and vnprouided end,</l>
                  <l>Of this falſe Tod without prouiſion,</l>
                  <l>Example is, exhorting folke to amend,</l>
                  <l>For dread of ſuch and like confuſion.</l>
                  <l>For many now hath good profeſſion.</l>
                  <l>Yet not repentes, nor for their ſinnes weepe,</l>
                  <l>Bicauſe they thinke their luſty life ſo ſweete.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some bene alſo thorow conſueted and ryte,</l>
                  <l>Vanquiſht with carnall ſenſualitie,</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:180704:23"/>
                  <l> Suppoſe they be as for the time contryte,</l>
                  <l>Can not forbeare, nor fro their ſinnes flee:</l>
                  <l>Vſe drawes nature ſo in propertie,</l>
                  <l>Of beaſt and man, that needes they muſt do,</l>
                  <l>As they of long time haue bene vſde thereto.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Beware good folkes, and feare this ſudden ſhote,</l>
                  <l>Whiche ſmites ſort without any reſiſtaunce,</l>
                  <l>Attend wiſely, and in your hartes note,</l>
                  <l>Againſt death may no man make defence:</l>
                  <l>Ceaſe off your ſinne, remorſe your conſcience,</l>
                  <l>Obey vnto your God and ye ſhall wend,</l>
                  <l>After your death, to bliſſe withouten end.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <head>The Retoricall tale of the ſonne and heyre of the foreſayd Foxe called Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wars, alſo the Parlement of foure footed beaſtes, holden by the Lyon.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THis foreſayd Foxe, that dide for his miſdeede,</l>
               <l>Had not one Sonne was gotten rightuouſly,</l>
               <l>To be heyre by law that might ſucceede,</l>
               <l>Except one Sonne whiche in adultery,</l>
               <l>He gotten had by purchaſe priuily:</l>
               <l>And he gaue him to name father wurſt,</l>
               <l>That loude well pultry although he were curſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:180704:24"/>
               <l>It folowes ſtill by reaſon naturall,</l>
               <l>As degree by degree, of right compariſon:</l>
               <l>Of euill comes worſe: of worſe comes worſt of all:</l>
               <l>Of wrongfull getting comes falſe ſucceſſion.</l>
               <l>This Foxe baſtard of generation,</l>
               <l>Of very kinde behoued to be falſe,</l>
               <l>So was his Father and his Graundſir als.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As naturall ſeeking his meate by ſent,</l>
               <l>By chaunce he found his fathers carrion,</l>
               <l>Naked, new ſlayne, and to him as he went,</l>
               <l>Tooke vp his head, and on his knees fell downne,</l>
               <l>Thanking the Gods of that concluſion.</l>
               <l>And ſayd, now ſhall I walke ſince I am heyre,</l>
               <l>The boundes where thou were wont to repayre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fye couetous, vnkind, and venemous:</l>
               <l>The Sonne was glad he found his father dead,</l>
               <l>By ſudden ſhotte for deedes odious,</l>
               <l>That he might raigne and rage ſtill in his ſtead,</l>
               <l>Dreading nothing the ſame life to leade,</l>
               <l>In theft and robry, as did his father before,</l>
               <l>But to the end, attent he tooke no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet neuertheleſſe thorow naturall pittie,</l>
               <l>The Carrion vpon his backe he taeth,</l>
               <l>Now finde I well this Prouerbe true (quoth he)</l>
               <l>Still runnes the Foxe, as long as he foote hath,</l>
               <l>So with the corps vnto a pit he gaeth,</l>
               <l>Of water full, and caſt him in the deepe,</l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:180704:24"/>
               <l> And to the Deuill he gaue his bones to keepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh fooliſh man plonged in worldlineſſe,</l>
               <l>To gather golde and other worldly meede,</l>
               <l>To put thy ſoule in payne and heauineſſe,</l>
               <l>To ritche thine heyre whiche hath but little neede:</l>
               <l>Haue be thy good once, he takes but ſmall heede,</l>
               <l>To execute, to do, to ſatiſfie,</l>
               <l>Thy latter will, thy debt, and legacie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Tod to reſt him, he paſſed till a crag,</l>
               <l>And there be heard a boyſtrous horne bloro,</l>
               <l>Whiche as he thought, made all the world wag:</l>
               <l>At laſt a Vnicorne came running below,</l>
               <l>Then ſtart he vp when he this heard and ſawe,</l>
               <l>With horne in band, a bill on breſt he bore,</l>
               <l>The goodlieſt Purſiuant that erſt was ſeene before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Unto a banke where he mought ſee aboute,</l>
               <l>On euery ſide, in haſt he gan him hie,</l>
               <l>Shot out his voyce full ſhrill and gaue a ſhowte,</l>
               <l>And on this wiſe, twice or thryce did crie:</l>
               <l>With that the beaſts in the fieldes thereby,</l>
               <l>All meruayling what ſuch a thing ſhould meene,</l>
               <l>Greatly agaſt, they gathered on a greene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Out of a wood a Bull ſo gan he brayde,</l>
               <l>And redde the text withouten tarrying,</l>
               <l>Commaunding ſilence, ſadly thus he ſayd:</l>
               <l>The noble Lion, of all beaſts the King,</l>
               <l>Greeting to God health euerlaſting.</l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:180704:25"/>
               <l> To brutall beaſts, and irration all,</l>
               <l>I ſend as to my ſubiects great and ſmall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My celſitude, and hie magnificence,</l>
               <l>Let you to wit, that euen incontinent,</l>
               <l>As to morow with Royall diligence,</l>
               <l>Vpon this hill to holde my Parlement,</l>
               <l>Straytly therefore I giue commaundement,</l>
               <l>For to appeare before my trybunall,</l>
               <l>Vnder all payne that may thereof befall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The morrow came, and <hi>Phebus</hi> with his beames,</l>
               <l>Conſumed had the miſty clowdes gray,</l>
               <l>The ground was greene and as gold it gleames.</l>
               <l>With graſſe growing goodly great and gay,</l>
               <l>The ſpice they ſpread to ſmell on euery ſpray:</l>
               <l>The Larke, the Mauis, and the Metle full hie,</l>
               <l>Sweetely can ſing ſkipping fro tree to tree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Two Leopards came with crowne of maſſiue gold,</l>
               <l>And ſo they brought it to the hils height.</l>
               <l>With Iaſpers, Ionet, and royals Rubies rold.</l>
               <l>And many diuers Diamondes ydight,</l>
               <l>With ſpeaken roapes a pauilion downe they pight.</l>
               <l>And there in throne ſate a mighty wilde Lion,</l>
               <l>In robe Royall, with Scepter, ſwoorde &amp; Corone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>After the tenor of the cry before,</l>
               <l>That all foure footed beaſts ſhould appeere in place,</l>
               <l>Is they commaunded were withouten more,</l>
               <l>Before the Lorde the mighty Lions grace,</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:180704:25"/>
               <l> And what they were to me, <hi>Laurence</hi> tolde apace,</l>
               <l>As I ſhall rehearſe apart of euery kinde,</l>
               <l>As far as now occurreth to my minde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Minotaur a monſter maruelous,</l>
               <l>Bellerophon that beaſt of baſtardy,</l>
               <l>The Warwolf, and the Pegaſe perillous,</l>
               <l>Tranſformed by aſſent of Sorcery:</l>
               <l>The Linx, the Tyger, full of tyranny:</l>
               <l>The Elephant, and eke the Dromedary,</l>
               <l>The Camell with his crane necke, forth can carry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Leopard, as I haue tolde beforne,</l>
               <l>The Intlop, the Sparth forth can ſpeede,</l>
               <l>The paynted Panthor, and the Vnicorne.</l>
               <l>The Rayndeer run through tyuer, ruſh and reede,</l>
               <l>The iolly Gennet, and the gentill ſteede.</l>
               <l>The Aſſe, the Mule, the Horſe of euery kinde,</l>
               <l>The Do, the Roe, the horned Hart, the Hinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Bull, the Bore, the Bugle, and the Beare,</l>
               <l>The tame Cat, Wildecat, and the wild wood Swine,</l>
               <l>The hardbacke Hedgehogge, and pennde Porcupine,</l>
               <l>The crookehorne Goate, the ſilly Sheepe, the Swine,</l>
               <l>The wilde Ounce, the Buck, the halting Brocke,</l>
               <l>The Fowmart, with the Fybert forth can flocke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The gray Greyhou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with Sleuth hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d forth ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlide,</l>
               <l>With Dogges all, diuers and different,</l>
               <l>The Rat ran, the Glybard forth can glyde,</l>
               <l>The pilde Polcat, with the Weſill went,</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:180704:26"/>
               <l> The fine Fycho that hath furre, money vent.</l>
               <l>The Merten, with the Cony, and the Con,</l>
               <l>The Bowrabant, and eke the Lerion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Marmeſſet the Moule can lead,</l>
               <l>Bicauſe that nature denied had hir ſight,</l>
               <l>Thus dreſſed they all foorth for dread of dead,</l>
               <l>The Muſk, the little Mouſe with all hir might,</l>
               <l>With haſt ſhe hied vnto that hill of hight,</l>
               <l>And many kinde of beaſts I could not know,</l>
               <l>Before theyr Lord (the Lion) lowted low.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Seing theſe beaſts all at his bidding boun,</l>
               <l>He gaue a brayde and looked him about,</l>
               <l>Then flatlings to his feete they fell all downe,</l>
               <l>For dread of death, they drouped all in doute,</l>
               <l>He looked when that he ſawe them lowte,</l>
               <l>And bad them with a countenance full ſweete,</l>
               <l>Be not afrayde, but ſtand vpon your feete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I let you wit my might is mercyable,</l>
               <l>And hurtes none that are to me proſtrate,</l>
               <l>Angry, auſterne, and alſo vnamiable,</l>
               <l>To all that ſtande agaynſt my royall ſtate,</l>
               <l>I true of life all beaſtes that make debate,</l>
               <l>Againſt the might of my magnificence,</l>
               <l>See none pretende to quarrell in my preſence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My celſitude, and my hie maieſtie,</l>
               <l>With might, and mercy mingled ſhall be ay,</l>
               <l>The loweſt here I can full ſoone rayſe hie,</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:180704:26"/>
               <l> And make him Maſter ouer you all I may.</l>
               <l>The Dromedary if he will make deray,</l>
               <l>The great Camell though he were neere ſo crouſe,</l>
               <l>Can bring as lowe as the little Mouſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>See that within twenty myles where I am,</l>
               <l>The Kid goe fault by the Goates ſide,</l>
               <l>The Tod for his head looke not on a Lam,</l>
               <l>Nor no rauenyng beaſt, neither run nor ride.</l>
               <l>They couched all after this was cride,</l>
               <l>The Iuſtice bad the court for to beginne,</l>
               <l>The ſutes called, and forfaytes bring in.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Panthor with his paynted coate ſheene,</l>
               <l>Fenced the court as the law hyd,</l>
               <l>Then the Tod lurkt back for feare being ſeene,</l>
               <l>And ſtarte backe behind one, and ſo him hid,</l>
               <l>Pulling his beare piteouſly he cride,</l>
               <l>Quaking for dread, and ſighing can he ſay,</l>
               <l>Alas this hower, alas thus dollfull day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I wot this ſudden aſſembly that I ſee,</l>
               <l>Hauing the poynts of a Parlement,</l>
               <l>Is made to mar, ſuch miſdoers as mee,</l>
               <l>Therefore if I me ſhewe I ſhalbe ſhent:</l>
               <l>I will therefore goe and be abſent,</l>
               <l>To byde or flee, I wote not in fayth,</l>
               <l>All is a like, there folowes nought but death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Perplexed thus in hart can he meane,</l>
               <l>Throw falſhod how he might himſelfe defende,</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:180704:27"/>
               <l> His hood he drew right ore his tyne,</l>
               <l>And winking with one tye forth he wend,</l>
               <l>Halting he came that he might not be kend:</l>
               <l>And for dread that he ſhould be arreſt,</l>
               <l>He playde bo peep behinde fro beaſt to beaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O troubled ſpryte and cancred conſcience,</l>
               <l>Before a King rayning with rightuouſneſſe,</l>
               <l>Bluſhing cheekes, and ſhamefull countenance,</l>
               <l>Farewell thy fame, now gone is all thy grace,</l>
               <l>The Phiſnomy, the fauour of thy face,</l>
               <l>For thy defence, is foule and diſfigurate,</l>
               <l>Brought to the light by theſe tokens of late.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Be thou attached with thefte or with treaſon,</l>
               <l>For thy miſdeedes, wrongs, and wicked fay,</l>
               <l>Thy cheere changes <hi>Laurence,</hi> thou muſt looke don</l>
               <l>The worſhip of this worlde is gone thee away,</l>
               <l>Looke to this Tod, how he was in affray.</l>
               <l>And flee the ſinne of falſhood I thee reede,</l>
               <l>Where through there followes ſinne &amp; ſhameful deed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Appearing thus before their Lord and King,</l>
               <l>In order ſet all in ioy and myrth,</l>
               <l>Of euery kinde he made forth bring,</l>
               <l>And awfully he ſpake and thus put forth,</l>
               <l>If there was any kinde of beaſt on yearth,</l>
               <l>Abſent? and thereto made them deepely ſweare:</l>
               <l>And they ſayde none, except one Stud gray Mare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let ſende a meſſage vnto that Stud,</l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:180704:27"/>
               <l> The court then ſayde, now who ſhall it be,</l>
               <l>Come forth <hi>Laurence</hi> lurkyng vnder thy hood,</l>
               <l>A ha ſir mercy, lo I haue but one eye,</l>
               <l>Hurt in the hoghe, and crookt as ye may ſee:</l>
               <l>The Wolf is better farre in ambaſſage,</l>
               <l>And thereto learned, wiſe and ſage.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The King ſtoode vp, and ſayde hence away both,</l>
               <l>And they to goe without any tarrying,</l>
               <l>Ouer hill and dale, for feare of his wroth,</l>
               <l>And found the Mare at hir meate in the morning,</l>
               <l>Now (quoth the Tod) Madame come to the King,</l>
               <l>The court is called, and ye are found contumax,</l>
               <l>Let be <hi>Laurence</hi> (quoth ſhe) your courtly knax.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Miſtreſſe (quoth he) come, to the court ye muſt goe,</l>
               <l>The Lion hath commaunded ſo in deede,</l>
               <l>Sir Tod (quoth ſhe) go you and your felloe,</l>
               <l>I haue reſpite a yeare, and yee will reede,</l>
               <l>I cannot ſpell (quoth he) ſo God me ſpeede:</l>
               <l>Here is the Wolf a noble Clerke at all,</l>
               <l>And of this meſſage is made principall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He is autentike and a man of age,</l>
               <l>And he hath great practike of the chauncelery,</l>
               <l>Let him go looke and reade your priuiledge,</l>
               <l>And I ſhall ſtand and beare witneſſe you by.</l>
               <l>Where is thy reſpite (quoth the Wolf) on hie?</l>
               <l>Sir it is here vnder my boofe well hid,</l>
               <l>Holde vp thy heele (quoth he) and ſo ſhe did.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:180704:28"/>
               <l>Though he were blinded, with pride yet he preſumed,</l>
               <l>To looke downe low where that hir letter lay,</l>
               <l>With that the mare gyrt him vpon the gums,</l>
               <l>And ſtrake the Hat of his head away:</l>
               <l>Halfe out of life, lying downe there he lay.</l>
               <l>Alas (quoth <hi>Laurence) Lupus</hi> thou art loſt,</l>
               <l>His cunning (quoth the Mare) was worth ſome coll.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> (quoth ſhe) wilt thou looke on my letter,</l>
               <l>Since that the Wolf nothing thereof can win?</l>
               <l>Nay by S. Bryde (quoth he) me thinkes it better,</l>
               <l>To ſleepe in a whole, than in a hurt ſkinne.</l>
               <l>Once a ſcrole I fand, and this was written in,</l>
               <l>For fiue ſhillings I would not loſe all nor ſome,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Folix quem faciunt aliena pericula caucum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With broken ſkalpe, &amp; cheekes that were blouddy,</l>
               <l>This wretched Wolf wiping them as he went,</l>
               <l>Of amends inuenting to get remedy.</l>
               <l>To tell the King the caſe was his intent,</l>
               <l>Sir (quoth the Tod) byde ſtill vpon this bent,</l>
               <l>And fro your browes waſhe away this blood,</l>
               <l>And take ſome drinke for it will do you good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To fetch water this fraudefull Foxe fore,</l>
               <l>Sidelong abacke as though he were ſicke,</l>
               <l>And as chaunſt he met comming fro the moore,</l>
               <l>A trip of Lambe, dauncing on a dike,</l>
               <l>This traytour Tod this tyrant and this tikt,</l>
               <l>The fatteſt of the flocke he killed haes,</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:180704:28"/>
               <l> And eate his fill, ſo to the Wolf he goes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They dranke togither, and ſo there iourney takes,</l>
               <l>Before the King, ſoone kneeled on their knee,</l>
               <l>Where is the Mare? ſir Tod, was contumax.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Laurence</hi> ſayd, my Lorde, aſke not mee,</l>
               <l>Demaund of your Doctor of Diuinitie,</l>
               <l>With his redde Cap can tell you well inough:</l>
               <l>With that the Lion, and all the reſt lough.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tell on the caſe now <hi>Laurence</hi> let vs heare:</l>
               <l>This witty Wolf, quoth he, this Clerke of age,</l>
               <l>On your behalf he bad the Mare to appeare,</l>
               <l>And ſo ſhe alledged hir priuiledge,</l>
               <l>Come neare and ſee, and you ſhall haue your wage.</l>
               <l>Bycauſe he red hyr reſpit playne and wele,</l>
               <l>Yonder red bonnet ſhe raught him with hir heele.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lion ſayd, by yon cap I ſee then,</l>
               <l>This tale is true, who heede vnto it takes:</l>
               <l>The greateſt Clerkes are not the wyſeſt men,</l>
               <l>The hurt of one, happy the other makes:</l>
               <l>As they were talking of theſe mery knakes,</l>
               <l>And all the Court in mirth and in gam,</l>
               <l>In comes the Ewe, the mother of the Lam.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Before the Iuſtice on hir knees ſhe fell,</l>
               <l>Put out hir playnt on this wiſe wofully:</l>
               <l>This Harlot bore ſon, and this hound of hell,</l>
               <l>Deuoured hath my Lambe full doggedly,</l>
               <l>Within a mile, contrary to your crie,</l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:180704:29"/>
               <l> For Gods loue my Lorde giue me the lawe,</l>
               <l>Of this lurker: with that <hi>Laurence</hi> let draw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Byde (quoth the Lion) limmer, let vs ſee,</l>
               <l>If it be ſothe the ſilly Yewe hath ſayde,</l>
               <l>A ha ſoueraigne Lord, pleaſe your grace, quoth he,</l>
               <l>My purpoſe was with him for to haue playde,</l>
               <l>And cauſles he fledde as he had bene affrayde.</l>
               <l>For dreade of death ouer a hedge with miſchief,</l>
               <l>And brake his necke, thou lies, quoth ſhe, falſe thief.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His death by practiſe may be proued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith,</l>
               <l>Thy gory gums, and thy blondy ſnoute,</l>
               <l>The wooll, the fleſh, it ſtickes in thy teeth:</l>
               <l>That is euidence inough without doubte,</l>
               <l>The Iuſtice bid chooſe the queſt then about:</l>
               <l>And ſo they did, and found that he was falſe,</l>
               <l>Of murther, theft, and treaſon alſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They bound him faſt, the Iuſtice bad beliue</l>
               <l>To giue the dome, and take of all his claes,</l>
               <l>The Wolf that new made Doctor gan him ſhryne,</l>
               <l>So forth was led, and to the Gallowes him haes,</l>
               <l>And at the ladder foote his leaue he taes,</l>
               <l>The Ape was hangman, and bid him ſoone aſcend,</l>
               <l>And truſſed him vp, and thus he made his end.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>RIght as the miner in his mynerall,</l>
                  <l>Fayre gold with fire may from the lead wel win,</l>
                  <l>Right ſo vnder a Fable figurall,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:29"/>
                  <l> Sad ſentences may ſeeke, and after fine,</l>
                  <l>As dayly doth the Doctors of deuine,</l>
                  <l>That to our liuing full well can apply,</l>
                  <l>And paynt the matter out with Poetry.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Lion is the world by likelyneſſe,</l>
                  <l>To whom bowes, both Emperour and King,</l>
                  <l>And thinks of this worlde to get increaſe,</l>
                  <l>Minding dayly for to get more liuing,</l>
                  <l>Some for to rule, and ſome to racke and ring,</l>
                  <l>Some gathereth geare, ſome gold, ſome other good,</l>
                  <l>To win this world, ſome worke as they were wood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Mare is men of good condition,</l>
                  <l>As pilgrims walking in this wilderneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Approuing that for right religion,</l>
                  <l>Their God only to pleaſe in euery place.</l>
                  <l>Abſtract from this worldes wretchedneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Fighting with luſt, preſumption and pryde,</l>
                  <l>And from this worlde in minde are mortifide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Wolf I liken to ſenſualitie,</l>
                  <l>As when like brutall beaſtes we do accord,</l>
                  <l>Our mindes all to this worldes vanitie,</l>
                  <l>Liking take, and loue it as our Lord,</l>
                  <l>Flee faſt therfore, if thou wilt right remord:</l>
                  <l>Then ſhall reaſon rayſe, raigne and ring,</l>
                  <l>And for thy ſoule there is no better thing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hir hoofe I liken to the thought of dead,</l>
                  <l>Wilt thou remember man, that thou muſt die,</l>
                  <l>Thus mayſt thou breake ſenſualities head,</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:180704:30"/>
                  <l> And fleſhly luſt away fro thee ſhall flie,</l>
                  <l>Aſſoone as thou thy minde doeſt mortifie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Salomons</hi> ſaying thou muſt remember herein,</l>
                  <l>Thinke on thy end, thou ſhalt not gladly ſinne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Tod I lyken, to temptations,</l>
                  <l>Bringing to minde many thoughts vayne,</l>
                  <l>Aſſaulting man with ſweete perſwaſions.</l>
                  <l>And ready for to trap them in a trayne,</l>
                  <l>Yet if thou ſet, ſenſualitie neare ſlayne,</l>
                  <l>And ſodeyn death draw neare with pangs ſore,</l>
                  <l>They quickly goe, and tempteth them nomore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O mediator mercyfull and meeke,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſoueraigne Lord, and King celeſtiall,</l>
                  <l>Thy mercies moſt humbly we beſeeke.</l>
                  <l>Vs to defende fro payne and perils all,</l>
                  <l>And helpe vs vp to thy heauenly hall,</l>
                  <l>In glory where we may ſee the face of God,</l>
                  <l>And thus endes, the talking of the Tod.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <head>¶ <hi>The wofull tale of the playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tife Dogge, agaynſt the poore Sheepe, before Iuſtice Wolfe.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>ESopt a tale puts in memory,</l>
               <l>How that a Dogge, bicauſe that he was poore,</l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:180704:30"/>
               <l> Called a ſheepe to the Conſiſtory,</l>
               <l>For certayne bread fro him for to recouer:</l>
               <l>A crafty Wolfe was Iudge that time, and boore</l>
               <l>Auctoritie, and Iuriſdiction,</l>
               <l>And for the ſheepe ſent foorth a ſtrayte ſummon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For by the vſe and courſe and common ſtyle,</l>
               <l>On this maner made his citation:</l>
               <l>I maſter Wolf, partliſſe of fraude and guyle,</l>
               <l>Vnder the paynes of hie ſuſpenſion,</l>
               <l>Of great curſing and interdiction.</l>
               <l>Sir ſheepe, I chardge thee, for to appeere,</l>
               <l>And anſwere to Perry Dogge, before me heere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir Corby Rauen, was made a parratour,</l>
               <l>Who picked had, full many ſheepes eye,</l>
               <l>The chardge he taketh, and on the letters boure,</l>
               <l>Summond the Sheepe before the Wolf, that he,</l>
               <l>Peremptorly, within twoo dayes or three,</l>
               <l>To appeare vnder the paynes in the bill,</l>
               <l>To heare what Perry dogge, will ſay thee til.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſummons made before witneſſe inowe,</l>
               <l>The Rauen as to his office well offerth,</l>
               <l>Indorſed hath the writte: and on he flewe,</l>
               <l>The ſilly ſheepe for ſorow, durſt lay no mouth on erth</l>
               <l>Till he before the lawfull iudge apperth.</l>
               <l>The houre of cauſe, whiche that iudge vſed than,</l>
               <l>Was, when <hi>Heſperus</hi> to ſhewe his face began.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Foxe was Clerke, and notary in the cauſe,</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:180704:31"/>
               <l> The Kight, and the Crow at the barre could ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>As Aduocates expert in the lawes,</l>
               <l>The Dogges to pleade togither tooke in hand,</l>
               <l>Whiche were con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ederate ſtraytly in a band,</l>
               <l>Againſt the ſheepe for to procure ſentence,</l>
               <l>Though it were falſe, they had no conſcience.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Clerke called the Sheepe, and he was there,</l>
               <l>The Aduocates on this wiſe could propone,</l>
               <l>Of certayne bread worth fiue ſhillings or mere,</l>
               <l>Thou owes the Dogge, of whiche the terme is go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Of his owne head without Aduocate alone,</l>
               <l>The ſheepe innocently gaue anſwere in this caſe,</l>
               <l>Here I appeale fro the Iudge, the time, the place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This is my cauſe I will ſhewe in effect,</l>
               <l>The lawe ſayes, it is right perilous,</l>
               <l>To enter in plea before a iudge ſuſpect,</l>
               <l>And you ſir Wolf haue bene full odious</l>
               <l>To me, for with your tuſkes rauenous,</l>
               <l>Haue ſtayne full many kinſmen of mine,</l>
               <l>Therfore as iudge ſuſpect, fro you I do decline.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And to be brief, of this court ye members all,</l>
               <l>Both Aſſeſſors, Clerkes, and Aduocate,</l>
               <l>To me and mine, are enimies mortall,</l>
               <l>And ay hath bene as many Sheperds wate,</l>
               <l>The place I ſuſpect, the time is very late:</l>
               <l>Wherefore no Iudge ſhould ſit in Conſiſtory,</l>
               <l>So late at euen, I you accuſe for thy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:180704:31"/>
               <l>When that the Iudge on this wiſe was accuſed,</l>
               <l>He bad the parties chooſe with one aſſent,</l>
               <l>Two arbitrators, as in the lawe is vſed,</l>
               <l>For to declare, and giue arbitrement,</l>
               <l>Whether the Sheepe ſhould anſwere in iudgement</l>
               <l>Before the Wolf, and ſo they did agree,</l>
               <l>Of whome the names, ye ſhall ſhortly ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Beare, and Brocke, the matter tooke in hand,</l>
               <l>For to decyde, if this exception</l>
               <l>Was of no force, or lawfully might ſtand.</l>
               <l>And therevpon as Iudges they ſate doune,</l>
               <l>And helde along while diſputation,</l>
               <l>Seeking full many decrees of the lawe,</l>
               <l>And glozes alſo the veritie to knaw.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of Ciuill law volumes full many they reuolue,</l>
               <l>The Codies and Digeſters new and olde,</l>
               <l>Contrait, proſtrait argumentes they reſolue,</l>
               <l>Some obiecting, and ſome gan holde,</l>
               <l>For prayer or pryce trow ye they would be controld.</l>
               <l>But holde the gloſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and text of the decreis,</l>
               <l>As true Iudges, I beſhrew them ay that leis.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shortly to make an end of this debate,</l>
               <l>The arbytratours thus they ſwearen playne,</l>
               <l>The ſentence giuen, and proceſſe fulminate.</l>
               <l>The Sheepe ſhould paſſe before the Wolf againe,</l>
               <l>And end his plea, then was he nothing fayne,</l>
               <l>For fro this ſentence could he not appeale,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:32"/>
               <l> Now Clerkes I aſke, if this ſentence were wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſheepe againe before the Wolf appeard,</l>
               <l>Without Aduocate, abaſhedly could ſtand,</l>
               <l>Vp roſe the Dogge, and to the Iudge thus ſweard,</l>
               <l>A ſumme I payd to him, before in hand,</l>
               <l>For certaine bread, a witneſſe here doth ſtand.</l>
               <l>That wrongfully the ſheepe doth holde the bread,</l>
               <l>Whiche he denide, and there began to plead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when the ſheepe this ſtrife had conteſtate,</l>
               <l>The iuſtice in the cauſe forth gan proceede,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> the actes, and the proceſſe wrate,</l>
               <l>And thus the plea vnto the ende they ſpeede:</l>
               <l>This curſed court corrupted all for meede,</l>
               <l>Againſt good fayth, law, and eke conſcience,</l>
               <l>For this falſe Dogge pronounced the ſentence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo forthwith put it in execution,</l>
               <l>The Wolf charged the ſheepe without delay,</l>
               <l>Vnder the paynes of interdiction,</l>
               <l>The ſumme of ſiluer or the bread to pay.</l>
               <l>Of this ſentence, alas, what ſhall I ſay?</l>
               <l>Whiche condemned hath the ſilly innocent,</l>
               <l>And iuſtified the wrongfull iudgement.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſheepe dreading more the execution,</l>
               <l>Obeying to the ſentence: he could take,</l>
               <l>His way vnto a marchaunt of the towne,</l>
               <l>And ſolde the woolle that he bore on his backe,</l>
               <l>So bought the bread, and to the Dogge can make</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:32"/>
               <l> Ready payment, as it commaunded was,</l>
               <l>So naked and bare to the fielde can pas.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THis ſelly ſheepe may repreſent the figure,</l>
                  <l>Of poore commons that dayly are oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>By tyrannous men whiche ſettes all their cure,</l>
                  <l>By falſe meanes to make a wrong conqueſt,</l>
                  <l>In hope this preſent life ſhould euer leſt:</l>
                  <l>But all beguyld, they will in ſhorte tyme end,</l>
                  <l>And after death to laſting paynes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Wolf I liken to a Shryue ſtout,</l>
                  <l>Which byeth a forfayte at the Kings hand,</l>
                  <l>And hath with him a curſed aſſiſe about,</l>
                  <l>And endites all the poore men vpon land,</l>
                  <l>Or if the Baylife hath layd on him his wand,</l>
                  <l>Though he were true as euer were S. Iohn,</l>
                  <l>Hangd ſhall he be, or with the iudge compone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Rauen I lyken to a falſe Coroner,</l>
                  <l>Whiche hath a portion of the inditement,</l>
                  <l>And paſſes forth before the Iuſticiair,</l>
                  <l>All miſdoers to bring vnto Iudgement,</l>
                  <l>But looke if he was, of any true intent,</l>
                  <l>To ſcrape out Iohn and wryte in Will, or Wat,</l>
                  <l>And take a brybe at both, how like ye that.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of this falſe Tod of whiche I ſpake before,</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:180704:33"/>
                  <l>And of this fight, what they mought ſignifie:</l>
                  <l>Of their nature, as now I ſpeake no more,</l>
                  <l>But of this Sheepe and of his carefull crie,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall rehearſe: for as I paſſed by,</l>
                  <l>Where that he lay, I chanced to looke downe,</l>
                  <l>And heard him make fore lamentation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alas (quoth he) this curſed conſiſtory,</l>
                  <l>In middes of winter now a dayes is made,</l>
                  <l>When Boreas with blaſtes bitterly,</l>
                  <l>And harde froſtes, the floures downe can fade,</l>
                  <l>On bankes bare now may I make no bade:</l>
                  <l>And with that woorde into a buſhe he crap,</l>
                  <l>Fro colde weather, and froſtes him to hap.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Quaking for colde, ſore mourning ay among,</l>
                  <l>Caſt vp his eye vnto the heauens hight,</l>
                  <l>And ſayd, Lord God why ſleeps thou ſo long?</l>
                  <l>Walke; and diſcerne my cauſe grounded on right,</l>
                  <l>See how I am by fraude, maſtery, and ſlight,</l>
                  <l>Pilled full bare, and ſo is many a one,</l>
                  <l>Now in this worlde, right wonder wo begone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>See how this curſed ſonne of couetice,</l>
                  <l>Bought hath the Lawier, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke the lawe,</l>
                  <l>Now few or none will execute Iuſtice:</l>
                  <l>In fault of whom the poore man is ouerthrow,</l>
                  <l>The verity ſuppoſe, the iudge it know,</l>
                  <l>He is ſo blinded with affection,</l>
                  <l>Without dread, for might, he lets the right go downe</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:180704:33"/>
                  <l>Seeſt thou not (Lorde) this world ouerturnde is,</l>
                  <l>And who will change good Gold in Lead or Tinne,</l>
                  <l>The poore is pulled, the Lord may do no mis,</l>
                  <l>And Simony is holden for no ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Now is he glad with craft that moſt may winne:</l>
                  <l>Good neighbourhood is ſlaine, and pitty is ago,</l>
                  <l>Alas (good Lord) why lets thou it be ſo?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou lets it thus be for our great offence,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſendes vs trouble, and plagues ſore,</l>
                  <l>As hunger, dearth, great warre, or peſtilence,</l>
                  <l>But fewe amendes now their life therefore,</l>
                  <l>We poore people as now may do no more,</l>
                  <l>But pray to thee, ſince that we are oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>Here in this earth, graunt vs in heauen good reſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <div type="prologue">
               <head>¶ <hi>The exemplatiue tale of the Lion and the Mouſe: With the Authors Prologue before.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN mids of Iune, that ſweete ſeaſon,</l>
                  <l>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that fayre Phebus with his beames bright,</l>
                  <l>Had dryed vp the dew, fro dale and downe,</l>
                  <l>And al the land <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ade with his beames light,</l>
                  <l>In a morning betwixt midday and night,</l>
                  <l>I roſe, and put all ſlouth and ſleepe aſide,</l>
                  <l>And to a wood I went, alone without guyde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:34"/>
                  <l>Sweete was the ſmell of floures white and redde,</l>
                  <l>The noyſe of byrdes right delicious,</l>
                  <l>The Beuis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ong right aboue my head,</l>
                  <l>The ground growing with graſſe gratious,</l>
                  <l>Of all pleaſaunce that place was plenteous,</l>
                  <l>With ſweete odours, and byrdes hatmony,</l>
                  <l>The mornyng milde, my mirth was more for thy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Roſes redde growing on bankes could ryſe,</l>
                  <l>The Prymeroſe, Violet purple and blake,</l>
                  <l>To heare it was a heauenly Paradiſe,</l>
                  <l>Such myrth the Mauis, and the Merle could make,</l>
                  <l>The bloſſoms braue, brake vp in banke and brake,</l>
                  <l>The ſmell of hearbes and of the fowles cry,</l>
                  <l>Contending who ſhould haue the victory.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Me to conſerue fro the Sunnes heate,</l>
                  <l>Vnder the ſhadow of a Hawthorne greene,</l>
                  <l>I layde me downe among the floures ſweate,</l>
                  <l>So cladde my head, and cloſed both myne eyne,</l>
                  <l>On ſleepe I fell among theſe byrdes fine,</l>
                  <l>And in my dreame me thought came through the feld,</l>
                  <l>The fayreſt man that euer I beheld.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His gowne was of a cloth as whyte as milke,</l>
                  <l>His Iacket was of chamlet purpure browne,</l>
                  <l>His hood of Scarlet brod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red well with ſilke,</l>
                  <l>And hangyng wiſe vnto his girdle downe,</l>
                  <l>His bonnet rounde of the olde faſhion,</l>
                  <l>His bearde was whyte, his eyne were great and gray,</l>
                  <l>With lockes of heares, which on his ſhoulders lay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A roll of paper in his hand he bare,</l>
                  <l>A Swans penne ſtickyng vnder his eare,</l>
                  <l>An inkehorne with a pretty gilt pennayre,</l>
                  <l>A bagge of ſilke all at his gyrdle beare,</l>
                  <l>Thus was he goodly girded in his geare,</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:180704:34"/>
                  <l> Of ſtatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e large, and with a fearfull face,</l>
                  <l>Euen where I lay he came a ſturdy pace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſayd God ſpeede my ſonne: and I was fayne,</l>
                  <l>Of that good woorde and of his company,</l>
                  <l>With reuerence, I anſwerd him agayne,</l>
                  <l>Welcome father: and he ſate downe me by,</l>
                  <l>Diſpleaſe you not my good maſter, though I,</l>
                  <l>Demaund your byrth, your faculty and nome,</l>
                  <l>Why ye come here, or where ye dwell at home.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My ſonne (ſayd he) I am of gentill bloud,</l>
                  <l>My natiue land is Rome withouten nay,</l>
                  <l>In that towne firſt to the ſcholes I yeude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>In ciuill lawe ſtudied full many a day,</l>
                  <l>And now my wonning is in heauen for ay,</l>
                  <l>Eſope I hight, my writyng and my warke,</l>
                  <l>Is kend and knowen to many a cunning clarke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O maſter Eſope Poete Lawreat,</l>
                  <l>God wote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e are full decre welcome to me,</l>
                  <l>Are ye not he that all the Fables wrate,</l>
                  <l>Whiche in effect ſuppoſe they fayned be,</l>
                  <l>Are full of prudence and Moralitie?</l>
                  <l>Fayre Sonne (ſayd he) I am the ſelf ſame man,</l>
                  <l>God wote if that my hart was mery than.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſayd, Eſope my maſter venerable,</l>
                  <l>I you beſeech moſt intierly,</l>
                  <l>Ye would not deyne to tell a prety fable,</l>
                  <l>Concluding with a good Moralitie.</l>
                  <l>Shaking his head, he ſayd, my ſonne let be,</l>
                  <l>What doth it profite to tell a fayned tale,</l>
                  <l>When holy preachyng may nothing auayle?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now in this worlde my thinke right few or non,</l>
                  <l>Vnto Gods worde that hath deuotion,</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:180704:35"/>
                  <l> The eare is deaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, the hart is hard as ſton,</l>
                  <l>Now open ſinne without any correction,</l>
                  <l>The hart enclining to the earth adowne,</l>
                  <l>So ruſted is this world with canker blake,</l>
                  <l>That now my tales may little ſuccour make.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yes gentle ſir (ſayd I) for my requeſt,</l>
                  <l>Not to diſpleaſe your fatherhead, I pray,</l>
                  <l>Vnder the figure of ſome brutall beaſt,</l>
                  <l>A morall Fable that ye would dayne to ſay,</l>
                  <l>Who knoweth, not I may learne and beare away,</l>
                  <l>Something thereby, hereafter may auayle?</l>
                  <l>I graunt (quoth he) and thus begins his tale.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="fable_proper">
               <head>The ende of the Prologue, and here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins the Tale.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Lion at his pray was ouerrunne,</l>
                  <l>To recreate his limmes and to reſt,</l>
                  <l>Beking his breaſt and belly at the Sunne,</l>
                  <l>Vnder a tree lay in the fayre forreſt:</l>
                  <l>Then comes there a trip of myce out of their neſt,</l>
                  <l>Right mery and glad, all daunſing in their guiſe,</l>
                  <l>And ouer the Lion vaulted twiſe or thryſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He lay ſo ſtill, the Myſe weare not afeard,</l>
                  <l>But to and fro, ore him tooke their trace,</l>
                  <l>Some twirled at the muchachos of his beard,</l>
                  <l>And ſome ſpared not to clawe him on the face,</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:180704:35"/>
                  <l> Merry and glad thus daunced they a ſpace,</l>
                  <l>Till at the laſt, the noble Lion wooke,</l>
                  <l>And with his paw, the maſter mouſe he tooke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She gaue a crie, and all the reſt agaſt,</l>
                  <l>Their dauncing left, and hyd them ſoone elswhere,</l>
                  <l>She that was tane, cried and wept full faſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſayd, alas, the time that I came here,</l>
                  <l>Now am I tane a wofull pryſonere,</l>
                  <l>And for my gilte, muſt byde incontinent,</l>
                  <l>Of life or death to heare the iudgement.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then ſpake the Lion to that carefull mous,</l>
                  <l>Thou caytife wretch, and vile vnworthy thing,</l>
                  <l>Ouer malapert and eke preſumptuous,</l>
                  <l>Thou wert to make out ouer me thy tripping:</l>
                  <l>Kneweſt thou not I was both Lord and King,</l>
                  <l>Of beaſts all, yes, quoth the mouſe, I know,</l>
                  <l>But I wiſt not bicauſe y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lay ſo lowe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lord I beſeech thy kingly royalty,</l>
                  <l>Heare what I ſay, and take in patience,</l>
                  <l>Conſider firſt my ſimple pouertie,</l>
                  <l>And then thy might and hie magnificence:</l>
                  <l>See alſo how things done of negligence,</l>
                  <l>Neither of malice, nor of preſumption,</l>
                  <l>The rather ſhould haue grace and remiſſion.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>We were replete, and had great aboundance</l>
                  <l>Of all things ſuch as to vs belonged,</l>
                  <l>The ſweete ſeaſon prouoked vs to daunce,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:36"/>
                  <l> And make ſuch myrth as nature to vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>earned,</l>
                  <l>Ye lay ſo ſtill as though ye had bene ſtrangled,</l>
                  <l>That by my ſoule we wend ye had bene dead,</l>
                  <l>Els would we not haue daunced ore your head.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy falſe excuſe, the Lion ſayd agayne,</l>
                  <l>Shall not auayle one whit I to thee ſay,</l>
                  <l>I put the caſe I had bene dead or ſlayne,</l>
                  <l>And ſo my ſkinne bene ſtopped full of hay,</l>
                  <l>Though thou had found my figure in the way,</l>
                  <l>Bicauſe it bare the print of my perſone,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhouldſt for feare on knees haue falen downe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For thy treſpas thou can make no defence,</l>
                  <l>My noble perſon this to vilepend,</l>
                  <l>Of thy fellows, nor thy owne negligence,</l>
                  <l>For to excuſe thou can no cauſe pretend,</l>
                  <l>Therefore thou ſuffer ſhalt a ſhamefull end,</l>
                  <l>And death, ſuch as to treaſon is decreed,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the gallowes all hanged but the head<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay mercy Lord, now at thy grace I aſke,</l>
                  <l>As thou art King of all beaſts coronate,</l>
                  <l>Aſſwage thy wrath, and let it ouerpaſſe,</l>
                  <l>And make thy minde to mercy inclinate,</l>
                  <l>I graunt offence is done to thyne eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Wherefore I worthy am as now to die,</l>
                  <l>But if thy kingly mercy pardon me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In euery Iudge mercy and ruth ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</l>
                  <l>As aſſeſſors, and Colaterall,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:36"/>
                  <l> Without mercy iuſtice is cruelty,</l>
                  <l>As ſayed is in the lawes ſpeciall,</l>
                  <l>When rigour ſittes in the trybunall,</l>
                  <l>The equitie of law who may ſuſteyne?</l>
                  <l>Right few or none, leaſt mercy go betweene.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alſo ye know the honour triumphall,</l>
                  <l>Of all victory, vpon the ſtrength depends,</l>
                  <l>Of his conqueſt, whiche manfully in battell,</l>
                  <l>Throwe ieopardy of warre long defends,</l>
                  <l>What pryce or prayſe when the battayle ends,</l>
                  <l>Is ſayd of him that ouercomes one man,</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe to defend, whiche neyther may nor can.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A thouſand myſe to kill and eke deuoure,</l>
                  <l>Is litle manhood to a ſtrong Lion,</l>
                  <l>Full little worſhip ſhall ye winne therefore,</l>
                  <l>To whoſe ſtrength is no compariſon:</l>
                  <l>It will appayre ſome part of your renoume,</l>
                  <l>To ſlay a mouſe, whiche may make no defence,</l>
                  <l>But aſking mercy at your excellence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alſo it ſeemes, not your celfitude,</l>
                  <l>Whiche vſes dayly meates delicious,</l>
                  <l>To file your teeth or lippes with any bloud,</l>
                  <l>Whiche to your ſtomacke is contagious,</l>
                  <l>Vnholſome meate alſo, is a ſory mous,</l>
                  <l>And that namely vnto a ſtrong Lion,</l>
                  <l>Wont to be fedde with gentill veniſon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>My life is little warth, my death is leſſe.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:37"/>
                  <l> Yet and I li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, I may p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raduenture,</l>
                  <l>Supply your highneſſe being in diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>For oft is ſeene a man of ſmall ſtature,</l>
                  <l>Reſcued hath a Lord of great honour,</l>
                  <l>That was beſet and in poynt ouerthrowne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrow miſfortune, ſuch caſe may be your owne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When this was ſayd, the Lion his language,</l>
                  <l>Pawſed, and thought according to reaſon,</l>
                  <l>And made mercy his cruell yre aſſwage,</l>
                  <l>And to the mouſe graunted remiſſion:</l>
                  <l>Opened his paw, and ſhe on knees fell downe,</l>
                  <l>And both hir hands vnto the heauen heild,</l>
                  <l>Crying almighty God your grace euer ſheild.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When ſhe was gone, the Lion went to hunt,</l>
                  <l>For he had naught but liued by his pray,</l>
                  <l>And ſlewe both tame and wilde as he was wont,</l>
                  <l>And in the countrey, made many a great fray,</l>
                  <l>Till at the laſt the people fond the way,</l>
                  <l>This cruell Lion how that they mought take.</l>
                  <l>So of Hempon cordes ſtrong nets can they make.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And in a lane where be was wont to ryn,</l>
                  <l>With ropes rude fro tree to tree they hing,</l>
                  <l>So caſt a ring without wood and within,</l>
                  <l>With hornes faſt blowing, and hounds crying,</l>
                  <l>The Lion fledde, and throw the lane running,</l>
                  <l>Fell in the net, and ſo caught by chaunce,</l>
                  <l>For all his ſtrength could make no reſiſtaunce.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:37"/>
                  <l>Weltring about with hideous roring,</l>
                  <l>While to, while fro, while he might ſuccour get,</l>
                  <l>But all in vayne, it auayled him nothing,</l>
                  <l>The more he flong the faſter was the net,</l>
                  <l>The ropes rude were ſo faſt about him ſet,</l>
                  <l>On euery ſide, that ſuccour ſaw he none,</l>
                  <l>But ſtill lying, and mourning made his mone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O lamentable Lion lying here ſo law,</l>
                  <l>Where is the might of thy magnificence?</l>
                  <l>Of whom al brutall beaſts in earth ſtoode aw,</l>
                  <l>And dread to looke vpon thy excellence,</l>
                  <l>Without hope, or help, without ſuccour or de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence,</l>
                  <l>In bandes ſtrong here muſt I lie (alace)</l>
                  <l>Till I be ſlayne I ſee no other grace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There is no wight that will my harmes wreke,</l>
                  <l>Nor Creature, do comfort to my crowne,</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall me help? who ſhall my bands breake?</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall me put fro payne of this priſoun?</l>
                  <l>By that he had made this lamentation,</l>
                  <l>Through aduenture the little Mouſe come by,</l>
                  <l>And of the Lion heard the wofull cry.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And ſuddenly it came in till hir minde,</l>
                  <l>That it ſhould be the Lion by his cloſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſayd now were I falſe, and right vnkind,</l>
                  <l>But I quite of his goodneſſe ſome part, I ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>Thou did to me, and on hir wayes ſhe goes,</l>
                  <l>To hir fellowes, and on them faſt can crie,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:38"/>
                  <l> Come help, come help, and they came by and by.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lo (quoth the mouſe) this is the ſame Lion,</l>
                  <l>That grace graunted me when I was tane anon,</l>
                  <l>And now is faſt here bounden in pryſon,</l>
                  <l>Breaking his hart with great mourning and mone,</l>
                  <l>Without we him help, of ſuccour wotes he none,</l>
                  <l>Come helpe to quite one good turne for another,</l>
                  <l>And loſe him quickly: they anſwered yea good brother.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They tooke no knife, their teeth were ſharpe inough:</l>
                  <l>To ſee that ſight, forſoth it was great wounder,</l>
                  <l>How that they ran among the ropes tough,</l>
                  <l>Before, behinde, ſome aboue, ſome vnder,</l>
                  <l>And ſhore the ropes of the net in ſunder,</l>
                  <l>Then had him riſe, and he ſtart vp anon,</l>
                  <l>And thanked them, ſo on his way is gone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now is the Lion free from all daunger,</l>
                  <l>Looſe and deliuered to his libertie,</l>
                  <l>By little beaſts, and of ſimple power,</l>
                  <l>As ye haue heard, bicauſe he had pittie,</l>
                  <l>(Quoth I maſter) is there a Moralitie,</l>
                  <l>Of this fable? yea Sonne (he ſayd) right good,</l>
                  <l>I pray you ſir then, (quoth I) conclude.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AS I ſuppoſe this mighty gay Lion,</l>
                  <l>May ſignifie a Prince or Emperour,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:38"/>
                  <l> Any poteſtate, or any King with crowne,</l>
                  <l>Whiche ſhould be captayne, guyde and gouernour,</l>
                  <l>Of his people that takes no labour,</l>
                  <l>To rule, and ſtere, the land, and iuſtice keepe,</l>
                  <l>Without lying ſtill in luſtes, flouth, and ſleepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The fayre forreſt with leaues freſhe to ſee,</l>
                  <l>With foules ſinging, and floures fayre and ſweete,</l>
                  <l>Is but the worlde and his proſperitie,</l>
                  <l>As falſe pleaſaunce mingled, and care replete,</l>
                  <l>Right as the Roſe, with froſt and winter wete,</l>
                  <l>Fades, ſo doth the world and them deſaue,</l>
                  <l>Whiche in their luſtes moſt confidences haue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe little myſe are but the commontie,</l>
                  <l>Wanton, vnwiſe, without correction,</l>
                  <l>Their Lordes, and Princes, when that they ſee,</l>
                  <l>Of Iuſtice make no execution,</l>
                  <l>They dread nothing to make rebellion,</l>
                  <l>And diſobey: for why, they ſtande in no awe,</l>
                  <l>That makes them, their ſoueraigne not to knaw.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By this Fable ye Lordes of prudence,</l>
                  <l>May conſider the vertue of pietie,</l>
                  <l>And to remit ſometime a great offence,</l>
                  <l>And mitigate with mercy, crueltie,</l>
                  <l>Ofttimes is ſeene a man of ſmall degree,</l>
                  <l>Hath quitte a King eyther with good or ill,</l>
                  <l>As the Lord hath done, rigour or grace him till.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who knoweth not, how ſoone, a Lord of gret renown</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:180704:39"/>
                  <l> Rowling in worldly luſt and vayne pleaſaunce,</l>
                  <l>May be ouerthrowen, deſtroyde, and put downe,</l>
                  <l>Through falſe fortune? which of all variaunce,</l>
                  <l>Is hole miſtreſſe and leader of the daunce,</l>
                  <l>To vniuſt men, and blindes them ſo ſore,</l>
                  <l>That they no perill can prouide before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe rurall men that hanged hath the net,</l>
                  <l>In which the Lion ſuddenly was throwne:</l>
                  <l>Wayted alway amendes for to get,</l>
                  <l>(For hurt men, wrytes in the marble ſtone)</l>
                  <l>More to expound, as now I let alone,</l>
                  <l>Both King &amp; Lorde may well know what I meene,</l>
                  <l>The figure hereof, ofttimes hath bene ſeene.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When this was ſayd (quoth Eſope) my fayre childe,</l>
                  <l>I thee beſeeke, and all men for to pray,</l>
                  <l>That treaſon of this countrey be exilde,</l>
                  <l>And Iuſtice raigne, and Lordes keepe their ſay,</l>
                  <l>Vnto their ſoueraigne Prince both night and day:</l>
                  <l>And with that woorde he vaniſht, and I wooke,</l>
                  <l>So through the wood my iourney when I tooke.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <head>The notable tale of the preaching of the Swallow.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe hie prudence, and working maruelous,</l>
               <l>The profound witte of God omnipotent,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:39"/>
               <l> Is ſo perſite, and ſo ingenious,</l>
               <l>Excellent farre, aboue mans iudgement,</l>
               <l>For why to him all things are ay preſent,</l>
               <l>Right as it is or any tyme ſhalbe,</l>
               <l>Before the ſight of his Diuinitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore our ſoules with ſenſualitie.</l>
               <l>So ſettred are in this pryſon corporall,</l>
               <l>We may not clearly vnderſtand nor ſee,</l>
               <l>God, as he is, nor things Caleſtiall,</l>
               <l>Our darke and deadly corps naturall,</l>
               <l>Blindeth the ſpirituall operation,</l>
               <l>Like as a man were bounde in pryſon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In metaphiſlcke <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> doth ſay,</l>
               <l>That mans ſoule is like a backes eye,</l>
               <l>Whiche lurketh ſtill as long as light of day,</l>
               <l>And in the twylight commeth forth to flie,</l>
               <l>Hir eyes are weake, the ſunne ſhe may not ſee,</l>
               <l>So is our ſoule with fantaſie oppreſt,</l>
               <l>To know the things in nature manifeſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For God is in his power infinite,</l>
               <l>And mans ſoule is feeble and ouer ſmall,</l>
               <l>Of vnderſtanding weake and vnperfect,</l>
               <l>To comprehend him that contaynes all:</l>
               <l>None ſhould preſume by reaſon naturall,</l>
               <l>To ſearch the ſecretes of the Trinitie,</l>
               <l>But beleeue firmely, and let vayne reaſons be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet neuertheleſſe we may haue knowledging,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:40"/>
               <l> Of God almighty, by his creatures,</l>
               <l>That he is good, fayre, wiſe and benigne,</l>
               <l>Example take by theſe iolly ſtoures,</l>
               <l>Right ſweete of ſmell, and pleaſaunt of collours,</l>
               <l>Some greene, ſome blew, ſome purple, white, &amp; redde,</l>
               <l>Thus diſtributed by gifte of his godhed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The firmament paynted with Starres cleare,</l>
               <l>From eaſt to weſt rolling in cirkle round,</l>
               <l>And euery planet in his proper Spheire,</l>
               <l>In morning making harmony and ſound,</l>
               <l>The fire, the ayer, the water, and the ground,</l>
               <l>To vnderſtand is inough iwis,</l>
               <l>That God in all his workes witty is.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Looke well on the fiſh that in the ſeas be,</l>
               <l>Looke well in the earth all kinde of beaſtiall,</l>
               <l>The foules fayre ſo forcely they flee,</l>
               <l>Parting the ayre with winges great and ſmall,</l>
               <l>Then looke to man, that he made laſt of all,</l>
               <l>Like to his Image, and his ſimilitude,</l>
               <l>By this we know that God is faire and gude.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>All Creatures he made for the behoue,</l>
               <l>Of man and to his ſupportation,</l>
               <l>In this earth, both vnder and aboue,</l>
               <l>In number, weight, and due proportion,</l>
               <l>The difference of time and eche ſeaſon,</l>
               <l>Concordant to our oportunitie,</l>
               <l>As dayly by experience wee may ſee,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:40"/>
               <l>The Sommer with his iolly mantell of greene,</l>
               <l>With floures fayre to furre it, him hath ſent,</l>
               <l>Whiche <hi>Flora</hi> Goddeſſe of the floures Queene,</l>
               <l>Hath to that Lord as for his ſeaſon lent,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Phebus</hi> with his golden beames gent,</l>
               <l>Hath purfelled and painted pleaſantly,</l>
               <l>With heate, and moyſture, ſtilling fro the ſky.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then Harueſt hote, when <hi>Ceres</hi> that Goddeſſe,</l>
               <l>Hir Barnes bleſſed hath with aboundaunce,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Bacchus</hi> God of wines renued hes,</l>
               <l>The tonne pipes, in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Fraunce,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With wines wight, and lycours of pleaſaunce,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Copia temporis</hi> to fyll his horne,</l>
               <l>That neuer was full of wheat, nor other corne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then comes winter wanne, when auſterne <hi>Eolus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God of the winde with blaſtes boreall,</l>
               <l>The greene garment of Summer glorious,</l>
               <l>Hath all to rent, and reuen in peeces ſmall,</l>
               <l>Then floures fayre faded with fraſtes, muſt fall,</l>
               <l>And birdes iocond changing their notes ſweete,</l>
               <l>Still mourning, neare ſlayne with ſnow &amp; ſleate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The dales deepe with ſnow drowned is,</l>
               <l>Both hill and holt beled with froſtes hoore,</l>
               <l>And Larkes bene left bare of any blis,</l>
               <l>By wicked windes of the winter woore,</l>
               <l>All wilde beaſts then from the fields frore,</l>
               <l>Drawes for dread vnto their dennes deepe,</l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:180704:41"/>
               <l> Couching for colde in hooles them to keepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>After comes <hi>Ver,</hi> when winter is away,</l>
               <l>The Secretary of Sommer with his cell,</l>
               <l>When Columbine vp peares through the clay,</l>
               <l>Whiche fled was before with froſtes fell,</l>
               <l>The Mauis, and the Metle, begins to meil,</l>
               <l>The Larkes on loft, with other byrdes theyr ſowne,</l>
               <l>They ſpred abrode ouer dale and downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That ſame ſeaſon in a fayre morning,</l>
               <l>Right glad that bitter blaſles neare ago,</l>
               <l>Vnto the wood to ſee the flowers ſpring,</l>
               <l>And heare the Mauis ſing and byrdes mo,</l>
               <l>I paſſed forth, and looking to and fro,</l>
               <l>To ſee the ſoyle, that was right ſeſonable,</l>
               <l>Sappie, and to receyue all ſeedes able.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus paſſing on great myrth I tooke in minde,</l>
               <l>Of laborers to ſee the buſineſſe,</l>
               <l>Some making dikes, and ſome the plough can winde,</l>
               <l>Some ſowing ſeedes faſt fro place to place,</l>
               <l>The Harrowes hopping in the furrowes trace,</l>
               <l>It was great ioy for him that loues corne,</l>
               <l>To ſee them labour both at euen and morne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as I went along a banke thereby,</l>
               <l>In hart greatly reioyſing of that ſight,</l>
               <l>Vnto an hedge, vnder a Hawthorne hie,</l>
               <l>Of ſmall birdes there came a great flight,</l>
               <l>And downe quickly on the leaues light,</l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:180704:41"/>
               <l> On euery ſide about me where I ſtoode,</l>
               <l>Right maruellous and a great multitude.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Among the whiche a Swallow loude can cry,</l>
               <l>On that Hawthorne hie in the toppe ſitting,</l>
               <l>O ye birdes all heare me by and by,</l>
               <l>Ye ſhall well know, and ye will ponder one thing,</l>
               <l>Where daunger is or perill appearing,</l>
               <l>It is great wiſedome to prouide before,</l>
               <l>It to auoyde for feare it hurt you more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir ſwallow (quoth the Larke againe) and lough,</l>
               <l>What haue ye ſeene, that cauſeth you to dread?</l>
               <l>See ye yonder churle, quoth ſhe, beyonde you plough,</l>
               <l>Faſt ſowing hempe, and good Line ſeede:</l>
               <l>Yonder lint will grow in little time in deede,</l>
               <l>And thereof will this churle his nettes make,</l>
               <l>Vnder the whiche he thinkes vs to take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore my counſell is when that he is gone,</l>
               <l>At euen, and with our nayles ſharpe and ſmall,</l>
               <l>Out of the earth ſcrape that ſeede anone,</l>
               <l>And eate it vp, for if it growes we ſhall,</l>
               <l>Haue cauſe to weepe hereafter one and all,</l>
               <l>See we remedy it with Inſtante,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nam leuius laedit quicquid preuidimus ante.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For Clerkes ſayes, it is not ſufficient,</l>
               <l>To conſider that is before thine eye,</l>
               <l>But prudence is an inward argument,</l>
               <l>That makes a man, prouide and fore ſee,</l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:180704:42"/>
               <l> What good, what euill, is lyke for to be,</l>
               <l>Of euery thing behold the finall ende,</l>
               <l>And ſo from perill, the better him defend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Larke laughing thus the Swallow to ſcorne,</l>
               <l>Sayd ſhe fiſht long before the net,</l>
               <l>The childe is ſoone broke that is vnborne,</l>
               <l>All groweth not that in the ground is ſet,</l>
               <l>The necke to ſtoupe when it the ſtroke ſhall get,</l>
               <l>Is ſoone inough: death on thee faſt fall,</l>
               <l>Thus mocked they the Swallow one and all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Deſpiſing thus hir holſome document,</l>
               <l>The fowles forthwith tooke their flight anon,</l>
               <l>Some with their make into the field went:</l>
               <l>And ſome againe are to the greene wood gon,</l>
               <l>Thus vnder the tree they left me alone,</l>
               <l>I tooke my clubbe, and homeward colde it cary,</l>
               <l>As fearefully as I had ſeene ſome Fayry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus paſſing forth while Iune that iolly tide,</l>
               <l>And ſeedes that were ſowen earſt beforne,</l>
               <l>Were growen hie, that Hares might them hide,</l>
               <l>And alſo the Quayles craking in the corne,</l>
               <l>I moued forth betwixt midday and morne,</l>
               <l>Vnto the hedge vnder the Hauthorne greene,</l>
               <l>Where I before, the foreſayd birdes had ſeene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And as I ſtoode by aduenture and caſe,</l>
               <l>The ſame birdes as I haue ſayd you ere,</l>
               <l>I hope, bicauſe it was their haunting place,</l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:180704:42"/>
               <l> More of ſuccour, or yet more ſolitaire,</l>
               <l>They light adowne: and when they lighted were,</l>
               <l>The Swallow againe put forth a piteous pime,</l>
               <l>And ſayd, woe is him cannot beware in time.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O blinde byrdes and full of negligence,</l>
               <l>Vnmindefull of your owne proſperitie,</l>
               <l>Lift vp your ſight and take good aduertence,</l>
               <l>Looke to that lint that growes on yond le,</l>
               <l>That ſame is the thing forſoth, that we,</l>
               <l>As I ſayd earſt, ſhould roote out and kill,</l>
               <l>Now is it lint: we can do it none ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Go yet while it is tender and ſmall,</l>
               <l>And pull it vp, let it no more increaſe,</l>
               <l>My hart grones, my body quakes with all,</l>
               <l>Thinking on it I may not ſleepe in peace,</l>
               <l>They cried all, and bad the Swallow ceaſe,</l>
               <l>And ſayd yonder lint hereafter will do good,</l>
               <l>For lyne ſeedes to little birdes are foode.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We thinke when that yonder lint ſeede is ripe,</l>
               <l>To make vs feaſts and fill vs with the ſeed,</l>
               <l>Mauger the churle, and on it ſing and peepe,</l>
               <l>Well (quoth the Swallow) friends hardly beet,</l>
               <l>Do as ye will, but certayne ſore I dread,</l>
               <l>Hereafter ye ſhall finde all ſowre, and not ſweete,</l>
               <l>When ye are ſpitted on the churles ſpitte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The owner of yond lint a fowler is,</l>
               <l>Right crafty, and full of ſubtilty,</l>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:180704:43"/>
               <l> His pray full ſeldome time will he mis,</l>
               <l>But if we birdes all, the warer be,</l>
               <l>Full many of our kinne he hath cauſde to die,</l>
               <l>And thought it but a ſport to ſpill theyr blood,</l>
               <l>God keepe me fro him, and the holy roode.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe ſmall birdes hauing but litle thought,</l>
               <l>Of perill that might fall by aduenture,</l>
               <l>The counceil of the Swallow ſet at nought,</l>
               <l>But tooke their flight and forth togither fure,</l>
               <l>Some to the wood, ſome marched to the moure,</l>
               <l>I tooke my ſtaffe, when this was ſayd and done,</l>
               <l>And walked home for it drew neare to none.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lint riped, the Carle puld the lyne,</l>
               <l>Rippilt the bowels, and in boundles it ſet,</l>
               <l>It ſteeped in water and dryed it fine,</l>
               <l>And with a betell knocked it, and bet,</l>
               <l>So ſwingled it well and hekled it in the flet,</l>
               <l>His wife it ſpan, and twinde it into threede,</l>
               <l>Of which the fowler nettes made in deede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Winter come, the wicked winde can blow,</l>
               <l>The woodes greene were faded with the weate,</l>
               <l>All things decayde with froſtes and with ſnow,</l>
               <l>Puddles and lakes made ſliddery with ſleate,</l>
               <l>The fowles fayre for fault they fall on feate,</l>
               <l>On bowes bare it was no boote to byde,</l>
               <l>But hied them to houſes them to hyde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some in the barne, ſome in the ſtake of corne,</l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:180704:43"/>
               <l> Theyr lodging tooke and made theri reſidence,</l>
               <l>The fowler ſaw, and great othes hath ſworne,</l>
               <l>They ſhould be tane truly for theyr expence,</l>
               <l>His nettes then he ſet with great diligence,</l>
               <l>And in the ſnow he ſhowled hath a playne,</l>
               <l>And heled it all ouer with chaf agayne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe ſmall byrdes ſeyng this chaf were glad,</l>
               <l>Thinkyng it had bene corne, they lited downe,</l>
               <l>But of the nettes no inkling they had,</l>
               <l>Nor of the fowlers falſe intention,</l>
               <l>To ſcrape &amp; ſeeke their meate they made them bowne,</l>
               <l>The Swallow on a little branch neare by,</l>
               <l>Dreading ſome guyle, thus lowd to them can cry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Into that chaf ſcrape whiles your nayles bleede,</l>
               <l>There is no corne ye labour all in vayne,</l>
               <l>Trowe ye yond churle for pitty will you feede,</l>
               <l>Na, na, he hath it here layde for a trayne,</l>
               <l>Remoue I reade you, or els ye wil be ſlayne,</l>
               <l>His nettes he hath ſet full priuily,</l>
               <l>Reddy to draw: in tyme beware, or ye die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great folies in him that puts in daunger,</l>
               <l>His life, his honour, for a thing of nought,</l>
               <l>Great follies in him, that will not gladly heare,</l>
               <l>Counſell in time, while it auayle him mought.</l>
               <l>Great folies in him, that hath nothing in thought,</l>
               <l>But things preſent: and after what may fall,</l>
               <l>Nor of the ende hath no memoriall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:180704:44"/>
               <l>Theſe ſmall birdes for hunger famiſht neare,</l>
               <l>Full buſily ſcraping for to ſeeke their foode,</l>
               <l>The counſell of the Swallow would not heare,</l>
               <l>Suppoſe their labour did them litle good.</l>
               <l>When ſhe their fooliſh hartes vnderſtood</l>
               <l>So indurate, vp in a tree ſhe flewe,</l>
               <l>With that this churle ouer them his nettes drew,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas it was great pitty for to ſee,</l>
               <l>That bloudy Boucher to beate the birdes downe,</l>
               <l>And ah to heare, when they wiſt well to die,</l>
               <l>Their carefull crie and lamentation,</l>
               <l>Some with a ſtaffe he ſtrake to earth on fowne:</l>
               <l>Of ſome the head he ſtrake, of ſome he brake the crag:</l>
               <l>Some halfe on liue he ſtopt into his bagge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when the Swallow ſaw that they were dead,</l>
               <l>Lo (quoth ſhe) theſe chances do ariſe,</l>
               <l>On them that will not take councell nor head,</l>
               <l>Of prudent men, or Clerkes that are wiſe,</l>
               <l>This great perill I tolde them more than thryſe:</l>
               <l>Now are they dead, wo is me therefore,</l>
               <l>She tooke hir flight, and I ſaw hir no more.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LO worthy folke, Eſope that noble Clerke,</l>
                  <l>A poet worthy to be Lawreate,</l>
                  <l>When he had leaſure, from more autentike werke,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:44"/>
                  <l> With other mo, this forſayd fable wrote,</l>
                  <l>Whiche at this time may well be applicate,</l>
                  <l>To very good morall edification,</l>
                  <l>Hauing ay ſentence according to reaſon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This carle, and bond of gentry ſpoliate,</l>
                  <l>Sowing this chaf, the ſmall byrdes to ſla,</l>
                  <l>It is the fende, whiche fro the angelike ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Exiled was as falſe Apoſtata,</l>
                  <l>Whiche day and night werieth not to ga,</l>
                  <l>Sowing poyſon in euery wicked thought,</l>
                  <l>In mans ſoule, which Chriſt ful deere hath bought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And when the ſoule, as into earth the ſeede,</l>
                  <l>Giues conſent vnto delectation,</l>
                  <l>Then wicked thoughts begins for to breede,</l>
                  <l>In deadly, ſinne whiche is damnation,</l>
                  <l>Reaſon is blinded with affection,</l>
                  <l>And carnall luſt, growes full greene and gay,</l>
                  <l>Through conſuetude haunted from day to day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Proceeding foorth by vſe and conſuetude,</l>
                  <l>Then ſinne ripes, and ſhame is ſet aſide,</l>
                  <l>The feende makes his nettes ſharp and rude,</l>
                  <l>And vnder pleaſaunce priuily them hide,</l>
                  <l>Then on the field he ſoweth chaf full wide,</l>
                  <l>Whiche is but droſſe and very vanitie,</l>
                  <l>Of fleſhly luſt and vayne proſperitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe little hirdes, wretches we may call,</l>
                  <l>Still ſcraping in this worldes vayne pleaſaunce,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:45"/>
                  <l> Greedy to gaher goodes temporall,</l>
                  <l>Which as the chaffe or droſſe without ſubſtaunce,</l>
                  <l>Little of auayle, and full of variaunce,</l>
                  <l>Like to the duſt, before the blaſt of winde,</l>
                  <l>Which whiſks away and maketh wretches blinde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Swallow whiche ſcaped is the ſnare,</l>
                  <l>The holy preacher well may ſignifie,</l>
                  <l>Exhorting folke to walke and ay beware,</l>
                  <l>From the nettes of our wicked enimie,</l>
                  <l>Who ſleepeth not but euer is ready,</l>
                  <l>When wretches in this world chaffe do ſcrape,</l>
                  <l>To draw his net, then they may not eſcape.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alas what care, what weeping is and woe,</l>
                  <l>When ſoule and body departed are in twayne?</l>
                  <l>The body to the wormes kitchin doth goe,</l>
                  <l>The ſoule to fire to euerlaſting payne,</l>
                  <l>What helpes then this chaffe, theſe goodes vayne,</l>
                  <l>When thou art put to Lucifers hyre,</l>
                  <l>And brought to Hell, and hangd in the fyre?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe hid nettes for to perceyue and ſee,</l>
                  <l>And this ſory chaffe, is wiſe vnderſtanding:</l>
                  <l>Beſt is beware in moſt proſperitie,</l>
                  <l>For in this world there is nothing laſting,</l>
                  <l>There is noman certayne how long ſhalbe his being,</l>
                  <l>How long his life ſhall laſt, nor how ſhalbe his end:</l>
                  <l>Nor after his death whether he ſhall wend.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pray we therefore whyle we are in this life,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:45"/>
                  <l> For foure things: the firſt, fro ſinne remoue,</l>
                  <l>The ſecond is, fro all warre and ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>The third is, perfect charitie and loue,</l>
                  <l>The fourth thing is and moſt for our behoue,</l>
                  <l>That is in bliſſe with Angels to be fellow,</l>
                  <l>And thus endeth the preachyng of the Swallow.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <head>¶ <hi>The mery tale of the wolf, that woldſhaue had, the Neckhering through the wyles of the Foxe, thnt beguiled the Carrier.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHylom there wound in a wildernes,</l>
               <l>(As mine Author expreſly can declare)</l>
               <l>A rauenyng Wolf, that liued vpon purches,</l>
               <l>On all beaſts and made him well to fare,</l>
               <l>Was none ſo bigge, about him he would ſpare,</l>
               <l>And he weare hongry, other for fauour or fayth,</l>
               <l>But in his wrath, he weried them to death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So happened him in rouing as he went,</l>
               <l>To meete a Foxe in mids of the way,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> him firſt ſawe and feard to be ſhent,</l>
               <l>And with a beke, he bad the Wolf good day,</l>
               <l>Welcome to me (quoth he) thou ruſſet gray,</l>
               <l>So bowed he downe, and tooke him by the hand,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:46"/>
               <l> Riſe vp <hi>Laurence</hi> I giue thee leaue to ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where haſt thou bene this long out of my ſight?</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt beare office, and my ſteward be,</l>
               <l>For thou can knap downe Capons in the night,</l>
               <l>And lurking lowe thou can make hennes die,</l>
               <l>Sir (ſayd the Foxe) that agrees not for me,</l>
               <l>And I am redde, if they ſee me afarre,</l>
               <l>At my figure, beaſt and birdes will ſkarre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay (quoth the Wolf) thou can in couert creepe,</l>
               <l>Vpon thy belly, and catch them by the head,</l>
               <l>And make a ſudden ſhowe vpon a ſheepe,</l>
               <l>So with thy weapons weary him to dead,</l>
               <l>Sir (ſayd the Foxe) ye know my robe is read,</l>
               <l>And therefore there will no beaſt abide me,</l>
               <l>Though I would be ſo falſe as for to hide me.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yes (quoth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Wolf) through hedge &amp; through buſh,</l>
               <l>Low can thou bowe to come to thine intent,</l>
               <l>Sir (ſayd the Foxe) ye wote well how I puſhe,</l>
               <l>And long fro them they will feele my ſent,</l>
               <l>Then will they eſcape, ſuppoſe I ſhould be ſhent,</l>
               <l>And I am aſhamde to come behind them,</l>
               <l>Into the field though I ſhould ſleeping find them.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay, quoth the Wolf, thou can come on the winde,</l>
               <l>For euery wrinke forſooth thou haſt a wyle,</l>
               <l>Sir, ſayd the Fox, that beaſt ye might call blinde,</l>
               <l>That might not ſcape then fro me a mile,</l>
               <l>How might I one of them that wayes beguyle?</l>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:180704:46"/>
               <l> My tipped two eares, and my two grey eyne,</l>
               <l>Makes me be knowen, where I was neuer ſeene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then, ſayd the Wolf, <hi>Laurence</hi> I heare thee lie,</l>
               <l>And caſtes for perrlis thy doings to defend,</l>
               <l>But all thy ſayings ſhall not auayle thee,</l>
               <l>About the buſh with wayes though thou wend,</l>
               <l>Wyly wil beguile himſelf at the latter end,</l>
               <l>To bowe at bidding, and bide not while thou breſt,</l>
               <l>Therefore I giue thee councell for the beſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir, ſayd the Fox, it is now Lent ye ſee,</l>
               <l>I cannot fiſhe for weting of my feet,</l>
               <l>To take a banſtakle, though we both ſhould die,</l>
               <l>I haue no other craft to winne my meate,</l>
               <l>But were it Eaſter that men ſhould pultry eat,</l>
               <l>As Kies, Lambe, or Capons then to ply,</l>
               <l>To beare your office I would full gladly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſayd the Wolf, in wrath weenſt thou w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyles,</l>
               <l>And with thy many mockes me to mate,</l>
               <l>It is an old dogge doubtleſſe that thou beguiles:</l>
               <l>Thou thinkes to draw the ſtraw before the cat.</l>
               <l>Sir, ſayd the Foxe God wote I meane not that,</l>
               <l>For and I did, it weare well donne that yee,</l>
               <l>In a hempen halter had tied me to a tree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now I ſee he is a foole parfay,</l>
               <l>That with his maſter falles in reſoning,</l>
               <l>I did but feele what that ye would ſay,</l>
               <l>God wote my minde was on another thing,</l>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:180704:47"/>
               <l> I ſhall fulfill in all things your bidding,</l>
               <l>What euer ye chardge me other night or dayes,</l>
               <l>Well (quoth the Wolf) I heare thee what thou ſayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But yet I will, thou make to me an othe,</l>
               <l>For to be true at all times and tyde,</l>
               <l>Sir (ſayd the Foxe) let no worde make ye wroth,</l>
               <l>For now I ſee that you haue me in dread,</l>
               <l>Yet ſhall I ſweare ſuppoſe it be nought neade:</l>
               <l>By <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and on payne of my head,</l>
               <l>I ſhall be true to you, whyle I be dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that a Carrier with pannier and creyles,</l>
               <l>Came ſinging forward: and <hi>Laurence</hi> could him ſpie?</l>
               <l>The Foxe the ſmell of the freſh herring feeles,</l>
               <l>And to the Wolf he roundes priuely</l>
               <l>Sir yonder are herring the carrier carries by,</l>
               <l>Therefore my counſell is to ſee for ſome wayes,</l>
               <l>To get ſome fiſhe againſt theſe faſting dayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Since I am ſteward, I would we had ſome ſtuffe,</l>
               <l>And ye are ſiluer ſicke, I know right weel,</l>
               <l>Though we would begge, yond very churliſt chuffe,</l>
               <l>He will not giue vs a herryng of his creell,</l>
               <l>Before the churle on knees though we would kneele,</l>
               <l>But yet I trow full quickly ye ſhall ſee,</l>
               <l>If I can craft to bleare the carles eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir, one thing is, and we get of you pelf,</l>
               <l>Ye muſt take trauayle and diligent be,</l>
               <l>For he that will not labour, and help himſelf,</l>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:180704:47"/>
               <l> In theſe dayes he is not worth a flee,</l>
               <l>For I thinke to worke as buſie as a bee,</l>
               <l>And ye ſhall follow a little afterwart,</l>
               <l>And gather vp herring, and that ſhalbe your part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that he caſt a compaſſe farre about,</l>
               <l>And layde him downe in mids of the way,</l>
               <l>As he weare dead he feynd without doubte,</l>
               <l>And then all a long vnlikely he lay,</l>
               <l>The white he turned vp of his eyne tway,</l>
               <l>His tong out hange a handbreath of his head,</l>
               <l>And ſtill he lay, as ſtife as he were dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Carrier found the Foxe and he was fayne,</l>
               <l>And to him ſelfe thus ſoftly can he ſay,</l>
               <l>At the next bayte in faith ye ſhal be flayne</l>
               <l>And of your ſkinne, I ſhall make mittens tway,</l>
               <l>He lept full lighty aboute him where he lay,</l>
               <l>And all the trace he tript on his toes,</l>
               <l>As he had hard a piper play he goes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Heare lieth the Deuill, quoth he, as big as a hogge,</l>
               <l>Such a fellon ſaw I not this ſeuen yeare,</l>
               <l>I trow ye haue bene tyred with ſome dogge,</l>
               <l>That makes you lie ſo ſtill withouten ſteare,</l>
               <l>Sir Foxe in faith you are well welcome heare,</l>
               <l>It is ſome wines bleſſing as farre as I know,</l>
               <l>For poultry picking that light on you I trowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There ſhall no pedler for purſe ne yet for gloues,</l>
               <l>Nor yet for points picke your pelft from me.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:48"/>
               <l> I ſhall of it make coufes to my loues,</l>
               <l>To keepe my handes warme where ere I be,</l>
               <l>To Flaunders ſhall it neuer ſayle the ſea,</l>
               <l>With that in hy he tooke him by the heels,</l>
               <l>And with one ſwage he flange him on his creels.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So by the head the horſe in haſt he tooke,</l>
               <l>The Foxe that ſaw, as crafty theefe alone,</l>
               <l>And with his teeth the ſtopple out he ſhooke,</l>
               <l>And ſo the herryng threw out one by one,</l>
               <l>Out of the creels he threw them downe anon,</l>
               <l>The Wolf was ware, and tooke vp ſpeedily,</l>
               <l>The Carrier ſang, hunt is vp, vp vpon hie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet at a brooke the Carrier lokt aboute,</l>
               <l>With that the Foxe lept quyte the creels fra,</l>
               <l>The Carrier would haue raught the Fox a rout,</l>
               <l>But all for nought, he wan his ſpurs that day,</l>
               <l>Then with a ſhoute thus can the Carrier ſay,</l>
               <l>Abide, and of neckherring ſhalt haue beſt,</l>
               <l>Is worth my horſe, the creels, and all the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now, quoth the Foxe, I ſhrew me and we meet,</l>
               <l>I hard what thou hight to do with my ſkinne,</l>
               <l>Thy hands ſhall neuer in thy coufes heet,</l>
               <l>And thou weare hanged carle and all thy kinne,</l>
               <l>Do forth thy market by me thou ſhalt not winne,</l>
               <l>And ſell thy herring thou haſt there, for hie pryce,</l>
               <l>Els thou ſhalt winne nought on thy marchandice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Carrier trembled for anger as he ſtood,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:48"/>
               <l> I am well worthy (quoth he) to loſe yond tike,</l>
               <l>That had nought in my hand to do ſo much good,</l>
               <l>As ſtaffe or ſticke, this fellon for to ſtrike:</l>
               <l>With that he lightly lept out ouer the dike,</l>
               <l>And cut downe a ſtaffe, for he was angry,</l>
               <l>That heauy was, and of the greene holly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that the Foxe vnto the Wolf could go,</l>
               <l>And fond him by the herrings where he lies,</l>
               <l>Sir (ſayd he then) haue I not playde the ſhrow:</l>
               <l>A wight man wanted neuer and he were wife,</l>
               <l>A hardy hart his hande for to ſuppriſe,</l>
               <l>(Than ſayd the Wolf) thou art a barne full bold,</l>
               <l>And wiſe at will, in good time be it tolde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But what was that the Carle cried on hie,</l>
               <l>And ſhooke his hand, quoth he, didſt thou not here?</l>
               <l>Sir (ſayd the Fox) that can I tell truly,</l>
               <l>He ſayd his neck herrings were in there,</l>
               <l>Knowes thou that herryng: ye ſir with good chere,</l>
               <l>And at the creele mouth I had thryce without doubt,</l>
               <l>The weyght whereof neare pluckt my tuſkes out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſothly ſir, might we that herring haue,</l>
               <l>It would be fiſh to vs theſe forty dayes:</l>
               <l>(Then ſayd the Wolf) now ſo God me ſaue,</l>
               <l>But to be there I would giue all my clayes,</l>
               <l>To ſee if that my weapons might it rayes,</l>
               <l>Sir (ſayd the Foxe) God wote I wiſht you ofte,</l>
               <l>When that my ſtrength might not beare it alofte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:180704:49"/>
               <l>It is a ſide of Salmon as it were,</l>
               <l>And coloured much like the Partrich eye,</l>
               <l>It is worth all the herrings ye haue there,</l>
               <l>Yee and wee had it ſir, is it worth ſuch three,</l>
               <l>Then, ſayd the Wolf, what counſell giues thou me?</l>
               <l>Sir, ſayd the Foxe, worke after my reede,</l>
               <l>And ye ſhall haue it, and take ye no dreede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Firſt ye muſt caſt a compaſſe farre about,</l>
               <l>So lay you downe in middes of the way,</l>
               <l>Both head, feete, and tayle, ye muſt ſtretch out,</l>
               <l>Hang forth your tong, and cloze your eyne tway,</l>
               <l>And ſee your head, on a harde place ye lay,</l>
               <l>And doubte ye no perill, that may appeere,</l>
               <l>But hold you cloſe, when that the Carle comes neere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And though ye ſee a ſtaffe haue ye no doubte,</l>
               <l>But holde you wounders ſtill, in that ſteede,</l>
               <l>And looke your tyne be cloſe as they were out,</l>
               <l>And ſee that ye ſhrinke neyther foote, nor head,</l>
               <l>Then will the hoorſon Carle trow ye be dead,</l>
               <l>And ſo in haſt, will take you by the heeles,</l>
               <l>As he did me, and ſwinge you in his creeles.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now, quoth the Wolfe, I ſweare thee by my thrift,</l>
               <l>I feare the Carrier carle he will me beare:</l>
               <l>Sir, ſayd the Foxe, on lofte he will you lift,</l>
               <l>Vpon his creeles, and do him little deare:</l>
               <l>But one thing ſothly I dare to you ſweare,</l>
               <l>Get ye that herring in ſome place ſicker,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:49"/>
               <l> Ye ſhall not neede go a fiſhing more while Eaſter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I ſhall ſay <hi>in principio</hi> ouer you,</l>
               <l>And croſſe your corps fro top to the fa,</l>
               <l>Wend when you will I dare warrant you,</l>
               <l>That ye ſhall die no ſudden death this day.</l>
               <l>With that the Wolfe girt him vp, and away,</l>
               <l>And caſt a compaſſe before the Carrier farre,</l>
               <l>So layd him downe in the way, or he came na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He layd the ſide of his head both hard and ſadde,</l>
               <l>So ſtretcht his forefeete fro him and his head,</l>
               <l>And hang his tong forth as the Foxe him bad,</l>
               <l>Alſo ſtill he lay as he had bene dead,</l>
               <l>Caring nothing of the Carles fauour nor fewd:</l>
               <l>But euer vpon the neckherring he thinkes,</l>
               <l>And quite forgets the Foxe and all his wrinkes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that the Carrier wauering as the winde,</l>
               <l>Came riding on the lode for it was light,</l>
               <l>Thinking on the Foxe that was behinde,</l>
               <l>Vpon what wiſe, reuenged on him he might,</l>
               <l>And at the laſt on the Wolfe he hath the ſight,</l>
               <l>Where be in length lay ſtretched in the gate,</l>
               <l>But if he lighted downe, or not, God wate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Softly he ſayd, I was beguyled once,</l>
               <l>Be I beguyld twice. I be ſhrewe vs bathe,</l>
               <l>That euill now ſhall light vpon thy bones,</l>
               <l>He ſhould haue had it that hath done me the ſkath,</l>
               <l>On hie he lifted the ſtaffe for he was wrath,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:50"/>
               <l> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it him with ſuch will vpon the head,</l>
               <l>That we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neere he ſowned to the dead.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Three battes he bore, or he his feete might finde,</l>
               <l>But yet the Wolf was wight and ran away,</l>
               <l>He might not ſee, he was ſo very blinde,</l>
               <l>Nor wit readily whether it were night or day.</l>
               <l>The Foxe beheld that ſeruice where he lay,</l>
               <l>And le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght aloft, when he the Wolf ſo ſees,</l>
               <l>Both deafe and ſtonniſhſt, fall ſowning on his knees.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He that with reaſon cannot be content,</l>
               <l>But couetes all, is likely all to loſe:</l>
               <l>The Foxe when that he ſaw the Wolf was ſhent,</l>
               <l>Sayd to himſelf, theſe herrings with me goes,</l>
               <l>I lye, or els he after got blowes,</l>
               <l>That found ſuch wayes his maiſter for to greeue,</l>
               <l>With all the fiſh thus <hi>Laurence</hi> tooke his leeue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Wolf he was, welneere done to dead,</l>
               <l>That vneth with his life away he ran<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>With the Baſtianado, broken was his head,</l>
               <l>The Foxe into his denne ſoone drew him than,</l>
               <l>That had betrayed his maiſter, and the man,</l>
               <l>The one wanted the herrings out of his creeles,</l>
               <l>The others bloud it ranne downe by his heeles.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THis tale is mingled with Moralitee,</l>
                  <l>As I ſhall ſhew ſomewhat or that I ceaſe,</l>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:180704:50"/>
                  <l> The Foxe, vnto the world may li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>The rauening Wolfe vnto man, but leaſe</l>
                  <l>The Carrier death, whom all men do oppreſſe,</l>
                  <l>That euer tooke life, through courſe of kinde muſt die,</l>
                  <l>As man and beaſt, and fowles aloft that flie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The world ye wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, is ſteward to the man,</l>
                  <l>Whiche maketh him haue no minde of dead,</l>
                  <l>But ſettes for winnyng all the craftes be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>The herring, I liken vnto the gold ſo r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad,</l>
                  <l>Whiche made the Wolfe in perill put his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ead,</l>
                  <l>Right ſo the golde, maketh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>andes and cit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies</l>
                  <l>With warre be waſted, dayly as men ſees.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And as the Foxe, diſſembling with guyle,</l>
                  <l>Made the Wolf weene to haue worſhip for euer:</l>
                  <l>Right ſo this worlde with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ayneglory for a while,</l>
                  <l>Flattereth with folke as they ſhould die neuer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet ſuddenly men ſeeth it oft diſſeuer</l>
                  <l>With them, that thinkes to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll at length the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke,</l>
                  <l>Death comes behind; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ps them by the neeke.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The getting of golde makes many ſo blinde,</l>
                  <l>That ſettes on auari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> theyr fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>citce,</l>
                  <l>That they forget the Carrier comes behinde,</l>
                  <l>To ſtrike them off, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſo ere they bee:</l>
                  <l>What is more darke than blinde proſperiter?</l>
                  <l>Wherefore, I councell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>che men to haue minde,</l>
                  <l>Of the Neckherring, interprete in this kinde.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <pb facs="tcp:180704:51"/>
            <head>The excellent tale of the wyly Laurence Foxe, that beguylde the couetous crafty Wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, with the ſhadow of the Moone.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IN elder dayes as Eſope can de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lare,</l>
               <l>There was a huſband man which had a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>low to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eare,</l>
               <l>His vſe was a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in morning to riſe rare,</l>
               <l>So it happened him, in ſtirring tyme of year<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Early in the morning to follow forth his fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Vnto the pſough only his gadman and he,</l>
               <l>His Oxen he bleſſed, with <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dicite.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The driuer cryed hop, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> on height,</l>
               <l>Well drawen my dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es ſo ſpake them fayre,</l>
               <l>The Oxen were luſty yong and light,</l>
               <l>And for fearceneſſe they layde the forrow for fayre:</l>
               <l>The huſbande then wore angry as a hare,</l>
               <l>So cried and caſt his pattell and great ſtones,</l>
               <l>The Wolfe, quoth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e mought haue y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all at ones.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But yet the Wolfe was neerer than he wen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>For in a buſh he lay, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> bathe,</l>
               <l>Among rough ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ub was at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urrowes end,</l>
               <l>And heard the height, then <hi>Laurence</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aught full rath,</l>
               <l>To take yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d offer, quoth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it were no ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath:</l>
               <l>Well, quoth the Wolfe, I hold thee her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my hand,</l>
               <l>The Carles woorde, as he were king ſhall ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Oxen waxte more rul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> at the laſt,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:51"/>
               <l> So after they lowſed when it was ſomewhat late,</l>
               <l>The huſband homeward with his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>attell p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt:</l>
               <l>Then ſoone the Wolfe came hopping in his gate,</l>
               <l>Before the Oxen, and ſhope to make debate:</l>
               <l>The huſband ſaw him and was ſomewhat agaſt,</l>
               <l>And backwarde with his beaſts, would haue paſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Wolfe ſayd whether dryues thou this pray?</l>
               <l>I chaleng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for none of them are thine,</l>
               <l>The ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at was in a fellon fray,</l>
               <l>And ſoberly to the Wolfe, anſwered ſine:</l>
               <l>Sir by my ſoule theſe Oxen are all mine,</l>
               <l>Therefore I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nuſe, now why y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould ſtop me,</l>
               <l>Conſidering I neuer, offended<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you truly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Wolfe ſayd Carle, didſt thou not giue this drift,</l>
               <l>Early, when thou was earing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n you banke?</l>
               <l>And is ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any thing mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er than gift?</l>
               <l>This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arrying, will loſe thee a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy thank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Far better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is freely for to giue a planke,</l>
               <l>Nor be compelled by force, to giue a mart,</l>
               <l>Fye on that gift, that comes not with good hart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir, quoth the huſband, a man may ſay in greefe,</l>
               <l>A woorde and call againe, if he aduiſe and ſee,</l>
               <l>I promiſe to ſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le, am I therefore a theefe?</l>
               <l>God forbid ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, all heights ſhould holden bee,</l>
               <l>Gaue I my hand or obligation, quoth he,</l>
               <l>Or haue ye witneſſe, or wryting here to ſhaw,</l>
               <l>Sir trouble me not, but go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and ſeeke the law.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:52"/>
               <l>Carle, quoth the Wolf, a Lord and he be leill,</l>
               <l>That ſhrinkes for ſhame, or doubtes to be reproued,</l>
               <l>His woorde is as fure as his feill:</l>
               <l>Fye on that man that is not true and loued,</l>
               <l>Thy argument is falſe, and eke contraried:</l>
               <l>For it is ſayd in Prouerbe, ye may ſee,</l>
               <l>All other vertues is nought worth a flee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir ſayd the huſband, remember this thing,</l>
               <l>A true man is not taken at half a woorde here,</l>
               <l>I may ſay, and vnſay, I am not a king:</l>
               <l>Where is your witneſſe, I promiſd you this geare?</l>
               <l>Than ſayde the Wolfe, therefore he ſhall come neare,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> (quoth he) come out of that ſhawe,</l>
               <l>And ſay nothing but as thou heard and ſawe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> came louring, for he loude neuer light,</l>
               <l>And ſoone appeared before them in that place,</l>
               <l>The man laughed not, when he ſaw that ſight:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> (quoth the Wolf) thou muſt declare the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace,</l>
               <l>Whereof we ſhall ſhew the truth in ſhort ſpace,</l>
               <l>I haue called thee true witneſſe to beare,</l>
               <l>What heard thou, this man promiſſe me here.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir ſayd the Tod, I cannot haſtily,</l>
               <l>So ſoone as now giue ſentence finall,</l>
               <l>But would you both ſubmit you here to me,</l>
               <l>To ſtande to my decree perpetuall,</l>
               <l>To pleaſe both I ſhould preue, if it may fall:</l>
               <l>Well (quoth the Wolf) I am content for me,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:52"/>
               <l> The man ſayd, ſo am I, how euer it be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſhew they forth and alledge without Fable,</l>
               <l>And both propones theyr plea to him compleet,</l>
               <l>(Quoth <hi>Laurence)</hi> now I am a iudge amiable,</l>
               <l>Ye ſhalbe ſworne to ſtand at my decreet,</l>
               <l>Whether hereafter ye thinke it ſower or ſweete:</l>
               <l>The Wolf put foorth his foote, the man his hande:</l>
               <l>And on the Tods tayle ſworne they are to ſtande.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then tooke the Tod the man a little beſide,</l>
               <l>And ſayd to him, friend, thou art in trouble brought:</l>
               <l>The Wolf will not forgiue thee one oxe hide,</l>
               <l>Yet would my ſelfe fayne help thee and I mought,</l>
               <l>But I am loth to hurt my conſcience in ought,</l>
               <l>Loſe not thy quarell in thine owne defence,</l>
               <l>This will not through withouten great expence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Seeſt thou not brybes beares all the ſway now?</l>
               <l>And giftes makes crooked matters hold euen?</l>
               <l>Sometimes an henne, ſaues a man a fow,</l>
               <l>All are not holy that heaues their handes to heauen:</l>
               <l>Sir ſayde the man, ye ſhall haue ſixe or ſeuen</l>
               <l>Right of the fatteſt hennes of all the flocke,</l>
               <l>I compt not all the reſt, leaue me the Cocke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am a iudge, quoth <hi>Laurence,</hi> then and lough,</l>
               <l>There is no brybes ſhall barre me fro the right,</l>
               <l>I may take Hennes and Capons well inough,</l>
               <l>For God is gone to ſleepe as for this night,</l>
               <l>Such ſmall things are not ſeene in his ſight,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:53"/>
               <l> Theſe hennes, quoth he, ſhall make thy matter ſure,</l>
               <l>With empty hand no man ſhould hawkes lure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Agreed thus, then <hi>Laurence</hi> tooke his leeue,</l>
               <l>As to the Wolfe he went into a linge,</l>
               <l>So pryuely he pluckt him by the ſleue,</l>
               <l>Is this in earneſt, quoth he, ye aſke ſuch thing,</l>
               <l>Nay by my ſoule I trow it be in ieſting,</l>
               <l>Then ſayde the Wolf, <hi>Laurence</hi> why fayſt thou ſo?</l>
               <l>Thou heardſt his promiſſe thy ſelfe not long ago.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The height (quoth he) the man made at the plough,</l>
               <l>Is that the cauſe why ye the cattell craue:</l>
               <l>Was halfe in ieſt (ſayd <hi>Laurence</hi> then) and lough,</l>
               <l>Sir by the toode me thinkes that now ye raue,</l>
               <l>The Deuill at all one tayle that ye ſhall haue,</l>
               <l>Thinke you Ile take vpon my conſcience,</l>
               <l>To do ſo poore a man as he offence?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet haue I commoned with the Carle, quoth he,</l>
               <l>We are accorded vpon this couenant,</l>
               <l>Quite of all claymes ſo ye will make him fire,</l>
               <l>Ye ſhall a Cabbock haue into your hand,</l>
               <l>That ſuch a one ſhall not be in all this land.</l>
               <l>For it is a Sommer cheeſe both freſh and good,</l>
               <l>He ſayth it weyes a ſtone downe by the rood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is that thy counſell, quoth the Wolfe, I do,</l>
               <l>That yonde Carle for a cheeſe ſhould be hei?</l>
               <l>Yea by my ſoule and I were ſworne you to,</l>
               <l>Ye ſhould no other counſell haue for me,</l>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:180704:53"/>
               <l> For goe ye to the moſt extremitee,</l>
               <l>It will not winne you worth a withered nepe,</l>
               <l>Sir trow ye not I haue a ſoule to keepe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well, quoth the Wolf, it is againſt my will,</l>
               <l>That yond cattel for one cheeſe ſhould goe quite,</l>
               <l>Sir (quoth the Tod) take it not in ill,</l>
               <l>For by my ſoule your ſelfe had all the witte:</l>
               <l>Then, ſayd the Wolfe, I byde no more to ſtitte,</l>
               <l>But I would ſee the Cabboke of ſuch pryze,</l>
               <l>For, ſayd the Tod, he tolde me where it lies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then hand in hand, they walked to an hill,</l>
               <l>The huſband towardes his houſe hath ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the way,</l>
               <l>For he was glad be ſeaped from their ill,</l>
               <l>And on his feete did walke while once did the day:</l>
               <l>Now will we turne vnto the other t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay,</l>
               <l>Through woodes waſt theſe freekes forth can fore,</l>
               <l>Fro buſhe to buſhe, till neere midnight and more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> was euer remembring vpon wrinkes,</l>
               <l>And ſuttilties, the Wolfe for to beguile,</l>
               <l>That he had promiſt a cheefe, be forethinkes.</l>
               <l>Yet at the laſt he findeth forth one wyle,</l>
               <l>That to himſelfe ſoftly could he ſmyle:</l>
               <l>The Wolfe ſayes, <hi>Laurence</hi> thou playes belly blinde,</l>
               <l>We ſeeke all night, but nothing can we finde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir, ſayd the Tod, we are at it almoſt,</l>
               <l>Softe you a little, and ye ſhall ſee it ſoone,</l>
               <l>Then to a mannour place they hied in haſt,</l>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:180704:54"/>
               <l> The night was light and fayre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hone the moone:</l>
               <l>Then to a draw well theſe Senyors both are come,</l>
               <l>Where that two b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ckets hang <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uerall, it was ſo,</l>
               <l>As one came vp, an other downe would go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ow of the Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e in the well,</l>
               <l>Sir, ſayd <hi>Laurence,</hi> once ye ſhall finde me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eill,</l>
               <l>Now ſee yt not the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe that I you tell,</l>
               <l>White as any milke and round as any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ele,</l>
               <l>He hangd it yonder that no man ſhould it ſteele,</l>
               <l>Sir truſt me well, the cabboke ye ſee hing,</l>
               <l>Might be a preſent to a Lorde or King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay, quoth the Wolf, might I this cabbok haue,</l>
               <l>On the dry land as I it yonder ſee,</l>
               <l>I would qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te clayme the Carle of all I eraue:</l>
               <l>His durty Ox<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re not for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>You were more me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te for ſuch a man as mee:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurence,</hi> quoth he, leape in the bucket ſoone,</l>
               <l>And I ſhall holde the one, while thou go downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laurence</hi> girde downe both ſoone and ſuttilly,</l>
               <l>The other bode abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and helde the flayle,</l>
               <l>It is ſo much, quoth <hi>Laurence,</hi> it maiſters me,</l>
               <l>On all my toes it hath not left one nayle:</l>
               <l>Ye muſt needes helpe vpwarde, and it hayle,</l>
               <l>Leape in the other bucket man haſtily,</l>
               <l>And come ſoone downe and helpe me by and by.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then lightly in the bucket leapt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owne,</l>
               <l>His weight ſtray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:180704:54"/>
               <l> The Tod came merily vp, the Wolf yeed downe,</l>
               <l>Then angerly the Wolf vpon him cryes,</l>
               <l>I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming thus downeward, why thou vpward hyes?</l>
               <l>Sir, quoth the Fox, thus fares it oft in towne,</l>
               <l>As one comes vp, ſo goeth another downe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then to the ground ſoone went the Wolf in haſt,</l>
               <l>The Tod lept on land as blyeth as any bell,</l>
               <l>And left the Wolf in water to the waſt,</l>
               <l>Who halde him out I wote not of the well:</l>
               <l>Here endes the text I haue no more to tell,</l>
               <l>Yet may men finde ſome good Moralitee,</l>
               <l>In this ſentence, though it a Fable bee.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe Wolf I liken to a wicked man,</l>
                  <l>Whiche doth the poore oppreſſe in ery place:</l>
                  <l>And pykes at them all quarels that he can,</l>
                  <l>By rigour, rape, and other wickedneſſe,</l>
                  <l>The Foxe the feend, I call into this caſe,</l>
                  <l>Egging all men to runne vnrightuous raynes,</l>
                  <l>Thinking thereby to locke him in his chaynes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The huſband may be cald a godly man,</l>
                  <l>With whom the fiend fault finds (as Clerkes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eedes)</l>
                  <l>Buſie to tempt him with all wayes that he can:</l>
                  <l>The hennes are workes, that fro firme faith proceeds,</l>
                  <l>Where ſuch ſprouts ſpreds, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil ſprit there not ſpeeds</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:180704:55"/>
                  <l> But wends vnto the wicked man againe,</l>
                  <l>That he hath loſt his trauell is full fayne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The woodes waſte, wherein was the Wolfe wilde,</l>
                  <l>Are wicked ritches, which all men gapes to get,</l>
                  <l>Who truſtes in ſuch truſtery, are oft beguylde,</l>
                  <l>For Mammon may be called the Deuils net,</l>
                  <l>Whiche Sathanas, for all ſinfull folke hath ſet:</l>
                  <l>Such proude pleaſure who ſets his truſt therein,</l>
                  <l>Without ſpeciall grace lightly can out wine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The cheeſe may be called couetice,</l>
                  <l>Whiche blometh broade in many mens eye,</l>
                  <l>Woe worth the well of that wicked vice,</l>
                  <l>For it is all but fraude and fantaſie,</l>
                  <l>Driuing all men to leape into that buttery,</l>
                  <l>That downeward drawes vnto the payne of hell,</l>
                  <l>Chriſt keepe all Chriſtians from that wicked well.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <head>¶ <hi>The mery tale of the wolfe and the Weather.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHylom there was, as Eſope can report,</l>
               <l>A Shepherd dwelling by a forreſt neare,</l>
               <l>Whiche had a Dogge that did him great comfort,</l>
               <l>Full ware he was to keepe his fold fro feare,</l>
               <l>That neither Wolf nor wildecat durſt appeare,</l>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:180704:55"/>
               <l> Nor Foxe on fielde, nor yet no other beaſt,</l>
               <l>But he them ſlewe, or chaſed at the leaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned it (as euery beaſt muſt ſleepe)</l>
               <l>This Dogge of ſudden ſickneſſe to be dead,</l>
               <l>But then God wote the keeper of the ſheepe,</l>
               <l>For very wo woxe wanner than the wead:</l>
               <l>Alas, quoth he, now ſee I no remead,</l>
               <l>To ſaue theſe ſelly beaſts that I now keepe,</l>
               <l>For why the Wolfe will weary all my ſheepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It would haue made a mans heart ſore to ſee,</l>
               <l>The ſelly ſhepherd make ſuch lamentation,</l>
               <l>Now is my dearling dead alas, quoth he,</l>
               <l>For now to begge my bread I may be bowne,</l>
               <l>With pike ſtaffe and with ſkrip fro towne to towne,</l>
               <l>For all the beaſtes before that bandoned weare,</l>
               <l>Will now returne againe, and all my ſhepe to teare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that a Weather ſtoutly ſtood on foote,</l>
               <l>Maſter, quoth he, make mery and be light,</l>
               <l>To breake your hart for bale, it is no boote,</l>
               <l>For one dead Dogge ye muſt not take ſuch flight,</l>
               <l>Go fetch him hither and flay his ſkinne ere night,</l>
               <l>So ſow it on me: and looke that it be meete,</l>
               <l>Both head, and necke, body, tayle, and feete.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then will the Wolfe beleeue that I am hee,</l>
               <l>For I ſhall follow him faſt where ere he fare,</l>
               <l>All hole the charge here I take vpon mee,</l>
               <l>Your ſheepe to keepe at midday late and rayre,</l>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:180704:56"/>
               <l> And he purſue, by God, I ſhall not ſpare,</l>
               <l>To follow him as faſt as did your dogge,</l>
               <l>So that I warrant, ye ſhall not want a hogge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Than ſayd the Shepherd, this comes of a good wit,</l>
               <l>Thy counſell is both good, faithfull, and true,</l>
               <l>Who ſayes a ſhepes a wretch, they lie of it:</l>
               <l>With that in haſt the dogges ſkinne of he flewe,</l>
               <l>And on the ſheepe right ſoftly could it ſewe,</l>
               <l>Than was the wether wanton of his weed,</l>
               <l>Now of the Wolf, quoth he, I haue no dreed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In all things he counterfayte the dogge,</l>
               <l>For all the night he ſtoode and tooke no ſleepe,</l>
               <l>So that long time there wanted not an hogge,</l>
               <l>So ware he was, and watchfull them to keepe,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Laurence</hi> durſt not looke vpon a ſheepe,</l>
               <l>For and he did, he followed him ſo faſt,</l>
               <l>That of his life he made him all agaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Was nother Wolf, wildeeat, nor yet Tod,</l>
               <l>Durſt come within the boundes all aboute:</l>
               <l>But he would chaſe them both throw rough and ſnot,</l>
               <l>Theſe baylefull beaſtes had of their liues ſuch doubte,</l>
               <l>For he was great and ſeemed to be ſtoute,</l>
               <l>That euery beaſt did dread him and eke feare,</l>
               <l>Without the wood that none durſt once appeare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It happened there an hungry Wolf to ſlyde,</l>
               <l>Out throw his ſheepe where as they did lie,</l>
               <l>I ſhall one haue, quoth he, what euer betyde,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:56"/>
               <l> Though I be weried, or els I will dle:</l>
               <l>With that a Lambe he got by and by,</l>
               <l>The reſt ſtart vp, for they were all agaſt,</l>
               <l>But (God wote) if the Weather folowed faſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Went neuer hound more haſtily from the hand,</l>
               <l>When he was runnyng moſt raſhly forthe roe,</l>
               <l>Nor went this weather ouer moſſe and ſtrand,</l>
               <l>And ſtopped neither at banke, buſke, nor bro,</l>
               <l>But followed ſtill, ay fiercely on his foe,</l>
               <l>With ſuche a drift, while duſt &amp; dirte ouerdraue him,</l>
               <l>And made a vowe to God that he would haue him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that the Wolfe let out his tayle at length,</l>
               <l>For he was hungry, and it drewe neare euen,</l>
               <l>And ſhope him for to runne with all his ſtrength,</l>
               <l>When he the weather ſo neare comming had ſeene,</l>
               <l>He dread his life, and he had taken bene,</l>
               <l>Therefore he ſpared neither buſke nor bogge,</l>
               <l>For well he knew the kindneſſe of the Dogge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To make him light he caſt the Lambe him fro,</l>
               <l>So lept ore leys &amp; ran through durt and myre,</l>
               <l>Nay (quoth the Weather) in fayth we part not ſo,</l>
               <l>It is not the Lambe, but thee that I deſire,</l>
               <l>I ſhall come neere for now I ſee thee tyre,</l>
               <l>The Wolfe ranne ſtill and durſt not looke behind him,</l>
               <l>But ay the neerer the weather he could winde him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Soone after that he followed him ſo neare,</l>
               <l>While that the Wolfe for feare befiled the field,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:57"/>
               <l> And left the way, and ran through buſhe and bryar,</l>
               <l>And thought within the woodes him for to ſhield,</l>
               <l>He ran ſtill reſtles, or els he muſt needes yeeld,</l>
               <l>The weather followed him out and in,</l>
               <l>While that a bryar buſh, tare rudely off the ſkin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Wolfe was ware and blinked him behind,</l>
               <l>And ſaw the weather come flinging through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bryer;</l>
               <l>So ſaw the dogge ſkin hanging on the lynd,</l>
               <l>Nay (quoth he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this ye that is ſo neere?</l>
               <l>Right now a hound, and now white as a fryer,</l>
               <l>I fled ore farre, and I had knowen the caſe,</l>
               <l>To God I vow that ye ſhall rewe this race.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What was the cauſe ye gaue me ſuch a catch?</l>
               <l>With that in haſt he tooke him by the horne,</l>
               <l>For all your wyles, you met once with your match,</l>
               <l>Suppoſe ye laught <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e all this yeare to ſcorne,</l>
               <l>For what treaſon haue ye this dogges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſkin borne?</l>
               <l>Maſter quoth he, but euen to play with you,</l>
               <l>I you require that ye none other trow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is this your ieſting in earneſt then, quoth he,</l>
               <l>For I am very fearefull and alſo flote,</l>
               <l>Come backe againe and I ſhall let you ſee.</l>
               <l>Then where the way was berayed he him brote,</l>
               <l>Whether call ye this fayre play or not?</l>
               <l>To ſet your maiſter in ſo fell afray,</l>
               <l>The which for feare thus filed hath the way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thryſe by my ſoule ye made me looke behinde,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:57"/>
               <l> And vpon my hotches my ſinewes may be ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne,</l>
               <l>For feardneſſe full ofte I field the winde,</l>
               <l>Now is this ye: nay but a Dogge I weene,</l>
               <l>My thinkes your teeth ore ſhort to be ſo keene,</l>
               <l>Bleſſed be the buſhe, that reft you your array,</l>
               <l>Cls flying burſten had I bene this day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir (quoth the weather) ſuppoſe I ran in hy,</l>
               <l>My minde was neuer to do your perſon ill,</l>
               <l>The flear gettes the folower commonly,</l>
               <l>In play or earneſt, proue who ſo euer will,</l>
               <l>Since I but played, be gratious me vntill,</l>
               <l>And I ſhall make my friendes to bleſſe your bones,</l>
               <l>For ſure good ſeruaunt will helpe his maſter once.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I haue oft times bene ſet in great affray,</l>
               <l>But by the roode ſo rayde yet was I neuer,</l>
               <l>As thou haſt made me with thy prety play,</l>
               <l>I ſhote behinde when thou ore tooke me euer,</l>
               <l>But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertaynly now ſhall we not diſſeuer,</l>
               <l>Then by the neckebone ſurely he him tooke,</l>
               <l>Or euer he ceaſt, and it in ſunder ſhooke.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ESope that Poet firſt father of this Fable,</l>
                  <l>Wrate this parable whiche is conuenient,</l>
                  <l>Bicauſe the ſentence was frutefull and agreeable,</l>
                  <l>In moralitie examplatiue prudent,</l>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:180704:58"/>
                  <l> Whoſe problemes bene very excellent,</l>
                  <l>Through ſimilitudes of figures to this day,</l>
                  <l>Giues doctrine to the readers of it for ay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here may thou ſee that ritches of array,</l>
                  <l>Will cauſe poore men preſumptuous for to bee,</l>
                  <l>Then thinke to holde of none be they as gay,</l>
                  <l>But counterfayte a Lorde in euery degree,</l>
                  <l>Out of knowledge in pryde they clime ſo hie,</l>
                  <l>That they will forbeare their better in no ſtead,</l>
                  <l>Till ſome man turne, their heeles ouer their head.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Right ſo in ſeruice other ſome exceedes,</l>
                  <l>And they haue wages, wealth and cheriſhing,</l>
                  <l>That they will be lightly Lordes in deedes,</l>
                  <l>And looke not to their bloud and ofſpryng,</l>
                  <l>But yet none knowes how long that rule will ring,</l>
                  <l>But he was wiſe that bad his ſonne conſider,</l>
                  <l>Beware in wealth, for the hall bench is right ſlyder.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore I counſell men of euery ſtate,</l>
                  <l>To know them ſelfe, and whom they ſhould forbeare,</l>
                  <l>And fall not with their better in debate,</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe they be as gallant in their geare:</l>
                  <l>It commeth not a ſeruaunt to bolde warre,</l>
                  <l>Nor clime ſo hie, while he fall of the lather,</l>
                  <l>But thinke vpon the Wolfe and on the Weather.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <pb facs="tcp:180704:58"/>
            <head>The wofull tale of the cruell <hi>Wolfe and the innocent Lambe.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>ACruell Wolfe right rauenous, and fell,</l>
               <l>Vpon a time paſt to a riuer,</l>
               <l>Deſcending from a rotch, vnto a well,</l>
               <l>To ſlake his thirſte dranke of the water cleare,</l>
               <l>So vpon chaunce, a ſelly Lambe came neare,</l>
               <l>But of his foe, the Wolfe nothing he wiſt,</l>
               <l>And in the ſtreame leaped to coole his thriſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They dranke both but not of one intent,</l>
               <l>The Wolues thought was all on wickednes,</l>
               <l>The ſilly Lambe was meeke and innocent,</l>
               <l>Vpon the ryuer in an other place,</l>
               <l>Beneath the Wolfe, he dranke a little ſpace,</l>
               <l>Whyle he thought good, thinking of none ill,</l>
               <l>The Wolfe him ſawe, and rampant came him till.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With grinning teeth, and fearefull angry looke,</l>
               <l>Sayde to the Lambe, thou caytife wretched thing,</l>
               <l>How durſt thou be ſo bolde to file the brooke,</l>
               <l>Where I ſhould drinke, with thy foule ſlauering?</l>
               <l>It were almes deede thee for to drawe and hing.</l>
               <l>That ſhould preſume, with thy foule lips ſo vile,</l>
               <l>To marre my drinke, and this fayre water file.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſelly Lambe quaking for very dread,</l>
               <l>On knees fell, and ſayd ſir with your leaue,</l>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:180704:59"/>
               <l> Suppoſe I dare not ſay, thereof ye lyed:</l>
               <l>But by my ſoule, I wote ye can nought preue,</l>
               <l>That I did aught in any, that ſhould you greue,</l>
               <l>Ye wote alſo that your accuſation,</l>
               <l>Beares no truth, and is againſt all reaſon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though I cannot, nature will me defend,</l>
               <l>And of the deede perfite experience,</l>
               <l>All heauy things muſt of themſelues deſcend,</l>
               <l>But if ſome things by force make reſiſtance,</l>
               <l>Then may the ſtreame in no way make aſcence,</l>
               <l>Nor runne backwarde: I dranke beneath you farre,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> the water therefore I did not marre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alſo my lippes, ſince that I was a Lam,</l>
               <l>Touched no thing that was contagious,</l>
               <l>But ſucked milke from pappes of my dam,</l>
               <l>Right naturall, ſweete, and alſo delicious,</l>
               <l>Well, quoth the Wolfe, thy language rigorous,</l>
               <l>Comes thee of kinde: ſo thy father to,</l>
               <l>Helde me at bay, till he no more could do.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He angred me, and then I could him warne,</l>
               <l>Within one yeare and if I broke my head,</l>
               <l>I would be venged on him or on his barne,</l>
               <l>For his ſpitefull and frowarde plead,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt doubtleſſe, for his deedes be dead.</l>
               <l>Sir it is wrong that for the fathers gilt,</l>
               <l>The fautleſſe ſonne ſhould puniſht be or ſpilt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Haue yt not heard what holy Scripture ſayes,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:59"/>
               <l> Spoken by the mouth of God almight?</l>
               <l>Of his owne deedes eche man ſhall beare the prayſe,</l>
               <l>As paynes for ſinne, rewardes for workes right,</l>
               <l>For my treſpaſſe why ſhould my ſonne haue plight?</l>
               <l>Who did the miſſe let him ſuſteyne the payne,</l>
               <l>A, A, (quoth the Wolfe) yet anſwereſt thou againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I let thee wit, when that the father offends,</l>
               <l>I will refuſe none of his ſucceſſion,</l>
               <l>And of his ſonnes, I well may take amends,</l>
               <l>Vnto the twenty degree deſcending downe,</l>
               <l>Thy father thought to make a ſtrong poyſon,</l>
               <l>And with his mouth, in my water did it ſpue,</l>
               <l>Sir, quoth the Lam, theſe two are nothing true.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The law ſayth, and ye will vnderſtand:</l>
               <l>There ſhould no man for wrong or violence,</l>
               <l>His aduerſary puniſh at his owne hand,</l>
               <l>Without proceſſe of law, and euidence,</l>
               <l>Whiche ſhould haue leaue to make lawfull defence,</l>
               <l>And therevpon ſummoned peremptorily,</l>
               <l>For to propone contrary, or reply.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Set me a lawfull court, I ſhall appeare,</l>
               <l>Before the Lion Lorde and true Iuſtice,</l>
               <l>And by my hand, I binde my faith right here,</l>
               <l>That I ſhall byde an vnſuſpect aſſiſe,</l>
               <l>This is the law, this is the inſtant guiſe.</l>
               <l>Ye ſhould pretend therefore and ſummons make,</l>
               <l>Againſt that day to giue reaſon and take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:60"/>
               <l>Nay (quoth the Wolfe) thou wouldſt intruſe reaſon,</l>
               <l>Where wrong and robry ſhould dwell in property,</l>
               <l>That is a poynt and parte of falſe treaſon,</l>
               <l>For to make ruth remayne with cruelty,</l>
               <l>By his woundes, falſe traytour, thou ſhalt die,</l>
               <l>For thy treſpaſſe and for thy fathers deede,</l>
               <l>With that anon he caught him by the head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſilly Lambe could do nothing but bleate,</l>
               <l>Soone was he dead, the Wolfe would ſhewe no grace,</l>
               <l>So dronke his bloud, and of his fleſh can eate,</l>
               <l>Whyle he was full and went his way apace,</l>
               <l>Of this murther what ſhall we ſay alace?</l>
               <l>Was not this ruth, was not this great pitty?</l>
               <l>To make this ſilly Lambe, without fault thus to die.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe poore people this Lambe may ſignifie,</l>
                  <l>As euil men, Marchants, and labourers,</l>
                  <l>Of whom this life is halfe a purgatory,</l>
                  <l>To winne their foode continually like miſers,</l>
                  <l>The Wolfe betokeneth falſe extortioners,</l>
                  <l>And oppreſſors of poore men as wee ſee,</l>
                  <l>By violence, crafte, or vſurie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Three kindes of Wolues in this world remaynes,</l>
                  <l>The firſt are falſe peruerters of the lawes,</l>
                  <l>Whiche vnder ſuttill termes falſhead mayntaines,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:60"/>
                  <l> As though all were Goſpell that he ſhowes,</l>
                  <l>But without brybe the poore he ouerthrowes,</l>
                  <l>Smoothering the right, making wrong proceede,</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch Wolues, helles fire ſhall be their meede.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O man of lawe let be thy futtletie,</l>
                  <l>With nycequips, and fraudes intricate:</l>
                  <l>And thinke that God in his Diuinitie,</l>
                  <l>The wrong &amp; right of all thy workes wate,</l>
                  <l>For prayer, pryce, for hye, nor lowe eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Of falſe quarrels ſee thou make no defence,</l>
                  <l>Holde with the right, hurt not thy conſcience.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An other kinde of Wolues ranenous,</l>
                  <l>Are mighty men, hauing full great plenty,</l>
                  <l>Whiche are ſo greedy and ſo couetous,</l>
                  <l>They will not let the poore in peace be,</l>
                  <l>Suppoſe he and his houſhold both ſhould dye</l>
                  <l>For fault of foode, no care will they make,</l>
                  <l>But ouer his head his houſe will they take.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O man without mercy what is in thy thought,</l>
                  <l>Were thou a Wolfe, and could vnderſtande,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt inough, the poore huſband right nought,</l>
                  <l>But little croppe of corne vpon a clot of lande,</l>
                  <l>(For Gods aw) how durſt thou take in hande,</l>
                  <l>And thou thy Barnes full, and yet doeſt egge,</l>
                  <l>To put him fro his liuing, and make them to begge.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The thirde Wolfe are men of heritage,</l>
                  <l>As Lordes that haue landes by Gods leaue,</l>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:180704:61"/>
                  <l> And lets out to poore men a village,</l>
                  <l>And for the time incomes doth receaue,</l>
                  <l>Ece halfe ſpent the time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>exeth him and berene,</l>
                  <l>With picked quarrels, for to make him fayne,</l>
                  <l>To flitte, or pay his income new agayne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His horſe, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>are, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e muſt lend to the Lord,</l>
                  <l>To drudge and drawe, in court or in carriage,</l>
                  <l>His ſeruaunt, or him ſelfe may not be ſpard,</l>
                  <l>To ſwing, or ſweat, withouten meate or wage,</l>
                  <l>Thus how he ſtandes in labour and bondage,</l>
                  <l>That ſcantly can he purchaſe bere or wine,</l>
                  <l>Courſe browne bread, or drinke that is thin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Haſt thou no pitty to make thy te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aunts ſweate,</l>
                  <l>In thy labour with faynt and hungry wome,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeſt, hath little good to drinke and eate,</l>
                  <l>With his meyny, at euen when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes home,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhouldſt feare for rightuous God his dome,</l>
                  <l>For it cryes vengeaunce to the Heauens hie,</l>
                  <l>To make poore men worke, without meate or f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O thou great Lorde that ritches haſt and rent:</l>
                  <l>Be not a Wolfe thus to deuoure the poore,</l>
                  <l>Thinke that nothing crue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l or violent,</l>
                  <l>May in this world perpetually endure,</l>
                  <l>Thus ſhouldſt thou beleeue, and certainely aſſure,</l>
                  <l>For to oppreſſe thou ſhalt haue as great payne,</l>
                  <l>As thou the poore, hadſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thine owne hand ſlayne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>God keepe the Lambe (whiche is the innocent,)</l>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:180704:61"/>
                  <l> From Wolues bit, and fell extortioners,</l>
                  <l>God graunt that wrangling men of falſe intent,</l>
                  <l>Be manifeſted, and puniſhed as offenders,</l>
                  <l>And God as thou all rightuous prayers heares,</l>
                  <l>To ſaue our Queene, and giue hir harte and hand,</l>
                  <l>All ſuch Wolues, to baniſh out of the land.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="fable">
            <head>¶ <hi>The tale of the wofull ende of the Paddocke and the Mouſe: ſhewing the miſchiefe of deſemblers.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>VPon a time (as Eſope coulde report)</l>
               <l>A little Mouſe came to a riuer ſide.</l>
               <l>She might not wade, hir legges were ſo ſhort<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Neyther could ſhe ſwim, ſhe had no horſe to ride,</l>
               <l>Of very force behinde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er to bide,</l>
               <l>And to, and fro, beſides the riuer deepe,</l>
               <l>She ran crying with many pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Helpe ouer, help ouer, this ſelly Mouſe can crie,</l>
               <l>For Gods loue, ſome body ouer the brim,</l>
               <l>With that a Paddocke in the water by,</l>
               <l>Put vp hir head, and on the banke gan clim,</l>
               <l>Whiche by nature could douke, and gayly ſwim,</l>
               <l>With voyce full ranke, ſhe ſayde on this manier,</l>
               <l>Good morne ſir Mouſe what is your errand heere.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:180704:62"/>
               <l>Seeſt thou (quoth ſhe) of corne yonde iolly plat,</l>
               <l>Of ripe Otes, of Barley, Peaſe, and Wheate,</l>
               <l>I am hungry, and fayne would be thereat,</l>
               <l>But I am ſtopped by this water great,</l>
               <l>And on this ſide I get nothing to eate,</l>
               <l>But harde nuttes, whiche with my teeth I bore,</l>
               <l>Were I beyond, my feaſt were much the more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I haue no boate, here is no marriner:</l>
               <l>And though there were, I haue no fraught to pay,</l>
               <l>(Quoth ſhe ſiſter) let be thy heauy cheere,</l>
               <l>Do my counſell, and I ſhall finde the way,</l>
               <l>Without Horſe, Bridge, Boate, or els gallay,</l>
               <l>To bring thee ouer ſafely, be not affeard:</l>
               <l>And not once to wet the compaſſe of thy beard.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I haue great wonder quoth the little Mous,</l>
               <l>How can thou flote, without feather or finne:</l>
               <l>This riuer is ſo deepe and dangerous,</l>
               <l>Me thinkes, that thou ſhuldſt drowned be therein,</l>
               <l>Tell me therefore, what faculty or gin,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt, to bring thee ore this water wan?</l>
               <l>That to declare, the Paddocke thus began.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With my two feete (quoth ſhe)long and brade,</l>
               <l>In ſteede of ores I rowe the ſtreame full ſtill,</l>
               <l>And though the bryme be perillous to wade,</l>
               <l>Both too and fro, I rowe at mine owne will,</l>
               <l>I may not drowne for why my open gill,</l>
               <l>Deuoydes all the water I receaue,</l>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:180704:62"/>
               <l> Therefore to drowne forſothe no dread I haue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Mouſe beheld then hir frowning face,</l>
               <l>Hir wrinkled cheekes, and hir lippes ſyde:</l>
               <l>Hir hanging browes, and hir voyce ſo harce,</l>
               <l>Hir lagring legges, and hir harſky hyde,</l>
               <l>She ran a backe and on the Paddock cryde,</l>
               <l>If I can any ſkill of Phiſnomy,</l>
               <l>Thou haſte ſome part of falſe villany.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For Clerkes ſayes, the inclination,</l>
               <l>Of mans thought, proceedes commonly,</l>
               <l>After the corporall complexion,</l>
               <l>To good or euill as nature will apply,</l>
               <l>A froward will and crabbed Phiſnomy,</l>
               <l>The old Prouerbe, is witneſſe of this <hi>lorum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Diſtortum vultum, ſequitur diſtortio morum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay (quoth the Frogge) that Prouerbe is not trew,</l>
               <l>For fayre things ofttimes are found infakin,</l>
               <l>The Blaberys though they be ſad of hew,</l>
               <l>Are gathered vp when Prymroſe is forſaken,</l>
               <l>The face may fayle, to be the hartes token,</l>
               <l>Therefore I finde this written in eche place,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhouldſt not iudge a man after his face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though I be irkſom for to looke vpon,</l>
               <l>There is no cauſe why I ſhould lacked be,</l>
               <l>Were I as fayre as iolly Abſolon,</l>
               <l>I am no cauſer of that great bewty,</l>
               <l>This difference in forme and qualitie,</l>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:180704:63"/>
               <l> Almighty God hath cauſed dame nature,</l>
               <l>To print and ſet in euery his creature.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of ſome the face may be full floriſhing,</l>
               <l>With ſilken tong, and cheere right amorous,</l>
               <l>With minde inconſtant, falſe, and varying,</l>
               <l>Full of deceyte, and meanes cautelous,</l>
               <l>Let be thy preaching (quoth the hungry Mouſe)</l>
               <l>And by what meanes now make me vnderſtand,</l>
               <l>That thou canſt help me vnto yonder land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou knoweſt, quoth ſhe, a body that hath neede,</l>
               <l>To help them ſelfe, ſhould many wayes caſt,</l>
               <l>Therefore go get a double twined threede,</l>
               <l>And binde thy legge to mine, with knottes faſt,</l>
               <l>I ſhall thee learne to ſwim, be not agaſt,</l>
               <l>(As well as I) As thou, then quoth the Mous,</l>
               <l>To proue that play, it were right perillous.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Should I be bound, and faſt, that now am free,</l>
               <l>In hope of helpe, nay then beſhrew my head,</l>
               <l>For I mought loſe, both life and libertie,</l>
               <l>If it were ſo who ſhould amend the deede?</l>
               <l>But if thou wilt ſweare to helpe me with ſpeede,</l>
               <l>Without fraude, or guyle, to bring me ore the flud,</l>
               <l>And without hurt or harme in fayth, quoth ſhe, good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She goyked vp, and to the heauen can cry:</l>
               <l>O Iupiter of nature God and King,</l>
               <l>I make an othe truly to thee, that I</l>
               <l>This littell Mouſe ſhall ouer this water bring,</l>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:180704:63"/>
               <l> This othe was made, the Mouſe without perceiuing,</l>
               <l>The falſe engine of this foule carping Pad,</l>
               <l>Toke threede, and bound hir legge as ſhe hir bad.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then foote for foote, they lap both in the brim,</l>
               <l>But in their mindes they were right different,</l>
               <l>The Mouſe thought of nothing, but for to ſwim,</l>
               <l>The Paddock for to drowne ſet his intent,</l>
               <l>When they in midway of the ſtreame nere went,</l>
               <l>With all hir force the Paddock preſſed downe,</l>
               <l>And thought the Mouſe without mercy to drowne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Perceyuing this, the Mouſe on hir can cry,</l>
               <l>Traytour to God and forſworne vnto me,</l>
               <l>Thou tookeſt vpon thy faith, right now, that I</l>
               <l>Without hurt or harme, ſhould ferried be and free,</l>
               <l>And when ſhe ſawe, there was but do, or dee,</l>
               <l>Withall hir might, ſhe forſt hir ſelfe to ſwim:</l>
               <l>And preſſed vpon the Todes back for to clim.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The dread of death, hir ſtrength made increas,</l>
               <l>And forced hir defende with might, and mayne,</l>
               <l>The Mouſe vpward: the Paddock downe can pres,</l>
               <l>Whyle to, while fro, whyle dowked vp againe,</l>
               <l>This ſilly Mouſe plunged into great payne,</l>
               <l>Can fight as long as breath was in hir breaſt,</l>
               <l>Till at the laſt ſhe cried for the prieſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fighting thus togither, the kight ſate on a twiſt,</l>
               <l>And to this wretched battell tooke good heede,</l>
               <l>And with a whiſke, or any of them wiſt,</l>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:180704:64"/>
               <l> He clenchet his talens betwixt them on the threede,</l>
               <l>So to the lande he flew with them good ſpeede,</l>
               <l>Glad of that catch, piping with many pew:</l>
               <l>So lowſed them, and without pity ſlew.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then bowelled them that butcher with his bill,</l>
               <l>And belly drawen full featly them he fleede,</l>
               <l>But all their fleſh, would ſcant be half a fill,</l>
               <l>And guttes alſo vnto that greedy gleede.</l>
               <l>Of their debate thus when I heard the reede,</l>
               <l>He tooke his flight and ouer the fieldes flaw,</l>
               <l>If this be not true, then aſke of them that ſaw.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="moral">
               <head>Moralitie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>MY brother if thou wil take aduertence,</l>
                  <l>By this Fable thou may perceyue and ſee,</l>
                  <l>It paſſes farre all kinde of peſtilence,</l>
                  <l>A wicked minde fraught with woordes fayre and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee,</l>
                  <l>Beware therefore with whome thou matcheſt thee,</l>
                  <l>For thee were better go to carte and plow,</l>
                  <l>And all thy dayes to delue in wet and drie,</l>
                  <l>Than to be matched with a wicked fellow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A falſe intent vnder a fayre pretence,</l>
                  <l>Hath cauſed many an innocent to die,</l>
                  <l>Great folly it is to giue ouerſoone credence,</l>
                  <l>To all that ſpeakes fayrely vnto thee,</l>
                  <l>A ſilken tong, an heart of cruelty,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:64"/>
                  <l> Smites more ſore than any ſhot of arrow,</l>
                  <l>Brother if thou be wiſe, I red thee flee,</l>
                  <l>To match thee with a fained froward fellow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I warrant thee alſo, it is great negligence,</l>
                  <l>To bind thee faſt, where thou were franke &amp; free,</l>
                  <l>When thou art bounde, thou can make no defence,</l>
                  <l>To ſaue thy life, nor yet thy libertie.</l>
                  <l>This ſimple counſel brother take of me,</l>
                  <l>And it to conne forth both early and late,</l>
                  <l>Better without ſtrife, to liue alone we ſee,</l>
                  <l>Than to be matched with a wicked mate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This holde in mind, right more I ſhall thee tel,</l>
                  <l>What by theſe beaſtes may be fygurate.</l>
                  <l>The Paddocke vſing in the floud to dwel,</l>
                  <l>Is mans body, ſwimming rare and late,</l>
                  <l>In this wretched world with cares implicate,</l>
                  <l>Now hy, now low, whiles plu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vp, whiles down,</l>
                  <l>Continually in peril, and ready for to drowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now dolorous, now glad as byrde on breere,</l>
                  <l>Now in freedome, now wrapped in diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Now hole and ſound, now dead &amp; brought on beer,</l>
                  <l>Now pore as Iob, now rolling in riches.</l>
                  <l>Now gownes gay, now ragges laide in preſſe,</l>
                  <l>Now full as peaſe, now hungry as the hounde,</l>
                  <l>Now hoyſt on wheele, now thrown vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:65"/>
                  <l> This litle mouſe, here knit thus by the ſhin,</l>
                  <l>The ſoule of man betoken may indeede,</l>
                  <l>Bounden, and from the body may not win,</l>
                  <l>While cruel death come breake of life the threede,</l>
                  <l>The which to drown ſhould euer ſtand in dread</l>
                  <l>Of carnall luſt, by the ſuggeſtion,</l>
                  <l>Which drawes the ſoule continually a downe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The water is the world aye weltering</l>
                  <l>With many waues of tribulation:</l>
                  <l>In which the ſoule and bodie be ſturring</l>
                  <l>Standing right different in their opinion,</l>
                  <l>The ſoule vpwarde, the body preaces downe,</l>
                  <l>The ſoule right faine would be brought ore ywis,</l>
                  <l>Out of this world, into the heauens bliſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Right is death, that cometh ſodainely,</l>
                  <l>As doth a theef, and endeth ſoone the battell:</l>
                  <l>Be vigilant therfore, and ſtill ready,</l>
                  <l>For mans life is brickle and aye mortall.</l>
                  <l>My friend therefore make thee a ſtrong wall,</l>
                  <l>Of faith in Chriſt: for death wil the aſſay,</l>
                  <l>Thou knowſt not when, euen morrow or midday.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Adew my friend: and if that any aſke</l>
                  <l>Of theſe Fables, ſo ſhortly I conclude,</l>
                  <l>Say thou I left the reſt, vnto the learneds taſke,</l>
                  <l>To make example, and ſome ſimlitude.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180704:65"/>
                  <l> Now Chriſt for vs that died on the rood,</l>
                  <l>Of ſoule and life, as thou art ſauiour,</l>
                  <l>Graunt vs to paſſe into a bleſſed houre.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <hi>Finiſhed in the vale of Ayleſburie the thirtenth of Auguſt. Anno Domini.</hi> 1574.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <head>THE EPILOGVE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BEhold ye men) Eſope that noble clerke</l>
               <l>Although of body yformed wondrous ill,</l>
               <l>His fables wrote with wiſdome deep and darke</l>
               <l>To ſtir our mindes (to good which had no will)</l>
               <l>By beaſtes and foules, he ſpake to warne vs ſtill,</l>
               <l>As Foxe, Woulfe, ſheepe, dog, cocke and henne,</l>
               <l>To ſtirre our mindes to liue on earth like men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Its writ of olde by authours that are paſt,</l>
               <l>That Eſope was crooke backt, great belly &amp; head,</l>
               <l>Crooke legged, ſplay foote, &amp; like a Cowe in waſt</l>
               <l>Yet vertuous of his life, as it is ſead,</l>
               <l>Whoſe good examples liues though he be dead,</l>
               <l>In eche mans mouth, and ſhall do ſtill for aye.</l>
               <l>Lo vertue brings forth fruite without decay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus as ye heare ill ſhapen of his body,</l>
               <l>Yet of his minde none perfecter then he:</l>
               <l>But marke his Sawes, and ye finde him no noddy,</l>
               <l>But perfect aye, as perfect loe may be,</l>
               <l>Who lendes you light good vertuous wayes to ſee.</l>
               <l>Then loue this worke, and and reade it at your will,</l>
               <l>I but eclipſe his tales of ſo great ſkill.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
